<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The paradise of delights. Or The B. Virgins garden of Loreto With briefe discourses vpon her diuine letanies, by way of meditation. For the comfort of all such, as be deuout vnto her; and desyre her holy patronage &amp; protection. By I.S. of the Society of Iesus.</title>
            <author>Sweetnam, John, 1581-1622.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 129 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853219</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853219</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18588</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13238)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18588)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 582:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The paradise of delights. Or The B. Virgins garden of Loreto With briefe discourses vpon her diuine letanies, by way of meditation. For the comfort of all such, as be deuout vnto her; and desyre her holy patronage &amp; protection. By I.S. of the Society of Iesus.</title>
                  <author>Sweetnam, John, 1581-1622.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 217, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the English College Press] Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XX [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.S. = John Sweetnam.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PARADISE OF DELIGHTS. OR The B. Virgins Garden of <hi>Loreto.</hi> With briefe Diſcourſes vpon her Diuine Letanies, by way of Meditation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the comfort of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as be deuout vnto her; and deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e her holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By I. S. of the Society of IESVS.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Fulcite me floribus, ſtipate me malis.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cant. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum, M.DC.XX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MOST WORTHY ENGLISH GENTLEMEN, OF THE SODALITY OF THE IMMACVLATE CONCEPTION OF THE EVER B. VIRGIN MARY, IN LOVAYNE.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MOST WORTHY,</salute>
            </opener>
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>OMNENVS the Emperour is moſt highly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ended by Venerable antiquity, for that after glorious conqueſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mous victory ouer his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yled enemies, he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d a beautyfull Image <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the B. Virgin in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phant Chariot, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>red for himſelfe; That
<pb facs="tcp:18588:4"/>the Mighty Citty of <hi>Rome,</hi> Lady and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of the VVorld, might vvitneſſe, hovv duely and faithfully h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did honour &amp; reuerence her, through vvhoſe ay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and aſſiſtance (next after God) he atchieued th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame. A greater victor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue you obtayned ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> farre more potent ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and your gratefu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mindes &amp; feruorous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions in aduaunci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:18588:4"/>the honor of the Bleſſed Queene of Angells, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ovverfull Empreſſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he vvorld, vvill not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a moſt faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ognizing of her ready help, to the full accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment of your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Conqueſts; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo yield a moſt ſvveet &amp; fragrant odour, of this preſent age, to all true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arted Catholikes; and leaue a moſt memorable example of your vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:18588:5"/>endeauours to all Poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seneca</hi> vvorthily vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,<note place="margin">Lib. de prouid. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that, <hi>Inter bonos vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros &amp; Deum amicitia eſt, conciliante virtute:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveene good men and God, there is a ſtraite band of friendship, by reaſon of Vertue. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it comes to paſſe, that by your Generous actes of vertuous life, hauing contracted, and (by your earneſt ſeeking to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce
<pb facs="tcp:18588:5"/>the honor of his Elected Mother) confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this perpetuall lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue of perfect Amity vvith God; there muſt needes follovv that fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endly &amp; familiar com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly comfort, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme conſent of harts, both vvith God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your ſelues, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vvhich they only are vvorthily to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, vvho haue deſerued
<pb facs="tcp:18588:6"/>to be are a part in this ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall harmony, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be made truely happy.</p>
            <p>My vnvvorthynes therfore finding you ſo highly eſteemed in this melodious Quire, doth preſent this little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe vnto you; not much vnlike to poore people, vvho vſe to offer trifling Nevv-yeares-giftes vnto Great men, thereby to make their vnvvorthy
<pb facs="tcp:18588:6"/>Preſents an humble pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of ſome greater guerdon, and revvard. So if my ſlender labours might gaine ſo much honour, and make me ſo happy as to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred in your deuout, &amp; much reſpected Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, I should thinke my ſelfe moſt aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatiſfied. This my vnpolished lynes doe humbly requeſt, not by any vertue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,
<pb facs="tcp:18588:7"/>but for her ſake of vvhom vve novv treate. In hope vvherof I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours ſincerely affected in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>I. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:7"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, If thou be of the Bleſſed num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe, vvhoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and proffit I ſeeke in this little Treatiſe; let me deſire thee to plucke of thy deceitful ſpectacles of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity,
<pb facs="tcp:18588:8"/>and peruſe my plaine lines vvith deuout ſimplicity; othervviſe thou art like to finde thy labour of as little effect, in regard of vvhat thou ſeekeſt of me, as I shal find my hopes of ſmall expectation, for vvhat I deſire to vvorke in thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moyſes</hi> vvith admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration did ſee the <hi>Bush,</hi> in vvhich Almighty God appeared, burning, but not conſuming, vvhich
<pb facs="tcp:18588:8"/>made him the more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to behold that great and vvonderous viſion; but yet vvas commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to plucke off his shooes before he might haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. The like counſell I find giuen by <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> to thoſe vvho curiouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to behold the diuin mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, vvhich the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall VViſdom of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God hath vvrought in this myſticall Bush, the moſt Bleſſed Virgin his
<pb facs="tcp:18588:9"/>Mother. Thou wilt not ſo much admire the <hi>Gedeon</hi> Fleece beſprinckled vvith devv, as to behold a vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man clad vvith the ſunne, yet not conſumed vvith ſo great an heate. <hi>Meritò quidem admiraris Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>&amp; curioſiùs deſideras in tueri;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. ſerm. in Apoc. <hi>12</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>verum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamen ſolue calceamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta de pedib us tuis, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolucra pone carnalium cogitationum, ſi acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere concupiſcas.</hi> Not
<pb facs="tcp:18588:9"/>vvithout cauſe thou doſt admire (O holy Moyſes) &amp; more curiouſly doſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to behold; but caſt of thy shooes from thy feete, and bridle the inordinate deſire of thy flesh, if thou deſire to approach.</p>
            <p>No curious conceite but a pure intention, no earthly affection, but true deuotion, no faygned loue, but a dutifull reſpect muſt bring thee to the preſence of this ſacred Queene, to the
<pb facs="tcp:18588:10"/>ſight of this blazing ſtarre, into the moſt eſteemed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the euer Bleſſed mother of God. Read ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vvith deſire of proffit, &amp; my beſt vvishes shalbe as my intentionis, that it may turne to the great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and his thrice happy Mother, and to the Eternall good of thy ſoule. And in thy beſt deuotions pray for me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:10"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE INTRODVCTION TO THE FOLLOWING MEDITATIONS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of mans wil is ſuch, that of neceſſity it requireth the help of the Vnderſtanding, to the due performance of
<pb facs="tcp:18588:11"/>her noble acts, according to that vulgar <hi>Axiome</hi> of Philoſophers, <hi>Nihil volitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quin praecognitum,</hi> Nothing can be deſired, vnleſſe it be firſt knowne, whereupon it comes to paſſe, that the Wil cannot work but according to the light that it hath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foreſaid vnderſtanding: and the greater that the knowledge is of the good apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, the more doth the affection of the Will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and kindleth an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire of the thing vve loue.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:11"/>
            <p> Wherfore my intended purpoſe in theſe preſent Meditations, being to ſtirre vp the harts of al that right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peruſe them, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend reſpect, and deuout affection vnto the euer bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and moſt happy Virgin Mother of God; I muſt firſt lay before your eyes, the greatnes of her excellent Vertues, &amp; ſingular graces (as farre as my weakenes shalbe able) that the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding being once fully poſſeſſed vvith an impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnable conceipt of her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable
<pb facs="tcp:18588:12"/>Perfections, the wil may be the more ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moued, to loue and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſo beautiful a creature.</p>
            <p>To this effect I haue made choice of her deuout Letanies of <hi>Loreto,</hi> wherin moſt admirable tytles, and moſt manifeſt arguments of her greatnes are propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto vs; by vvhich not only our Vnderſtanding, may be aboundantly enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with diuine conceits, but alſo our Will may be greatly inflamed with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous deſires. From which
<pb facs="tcp:18588:12"/>two well-grounded Roots, will ſpring the beautifull branch of Imitation, the chiefeſt and only ſcope of all vertuous myndes, and the laſt marke at which all true deuotion aymeth; and vvithout vvhich both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion is fruitles, or no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion at all, and the beſt purpoſes are without ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. Witnes that worthy ſaying of <hi>S. Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Virgin.</note> 
               <hi>Quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis Mariae exoptat praemium, imitetur exemplum,</hi> Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer deſireth the reward of the Bleſſed Virgin Mary,
<pb facs="tcp:18588:13"/>let him imitate her exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. And S. <hi>Bernard</hi> giueth vs to vnderſtand, that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect imitation of her excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertues muſt be the only conduict to conuey vnto vs her louing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours,<note place="margin">Bern. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s eſt.</note> 
               <hi>Vt impetres eius orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis ſuffragium, ne deſeras con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſationis exemplum,</hi> that thou mayſt attaine to thy deſired effect of her pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, leaue not to follow her laudable Conuerſation.</p>
            <p>Conſonant to this is the doctrine of the burning Lampe of Africke, &amp; shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:18588:13"/>light of the vvhole Church, S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who writing of the true feſtiuity of holy Martyrs, ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. ſerm. <hi>47.</hi> de Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> 
               <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eis Sanctorum in veritate festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uag audia celebrantur, qui ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Martyrum exempla ſequu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> By thoſe indeed feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall dayes of holy Martyrs are truly celebrated vvho follovv the examples of their vertues. <hi>Fidelis ſermo</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi>) <hi>&amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni acceptione dignus &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Tom. <hi>3.</hi> ſerm. de mart.</note> It is a faithfull ſaying and worthy to be receiued by all men, that we should imitate in
<pb facs="tcp:18588:14"/>our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe Saints whome we honour with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne veneration.</p>
            <p>And by reaſon of the excellent tytles which are moſt worthily giuen to the renowned Queene of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in theſe deuout Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, wherein her louing Children find exceeding Comfort and Delight; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue thought good to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyt le this ſmall worke, <hi>The Paradiſe of delights,</hi> or, <hi>the B. Virgins garden of Loreto.</hi> And for our better Collection, it will not be amiſſe to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine,
<pb facs="tcp:18588:14"/>a priuate Garden, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dorned with all kind of delightfull flovvers, amid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt which the B. Virgin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeth to vvalke, expecting the viſitation of her deereſt friends, and moſt deuoted Clyents. Vnto the gate of this myſticall garden, and Paradiſe, we muſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach with all humility, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be admitted to the pleaſant vievv of thoſe ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall flowers, whoſe dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty odours haue filled the whole world with their fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant ſmell. And if our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
<pb facs="tcp:18588:15"/>be gratiouſly granted by the glorious Queene of Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; her Angels there attending on her, humbly proſtrate before her ſacred feete, vve muſt deſire, that whatſoeuer we shall gather out of this delightſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, may be to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; glory of her ſweet Sonne leſus, to the increaſe of deuotion to her grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Selfe, and to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happynes of our owne ſoules Then may we begin vvith the firſt flovver of this heauenly Garden, or
<pb facs="tcp:18588:15"/>the firſt vvord of theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euout Letanies <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>IA,</hi> the moſt venerable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame of the euer Bleſſed &amp; moſt happy Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f which we may frame our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>editation; imploring firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er dayly ayde and aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance in the manner follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:16"/>
            <head>ORATIO SODALITATE a ſingulis in admiſſione recitanda.</head>
            <p>SANCTA Maria, Mate Dei &amp; Virgo, Ego N. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hodie in Dominam, Patronam &amp; Aduocatam eligo; firmiter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtatuo ac propono, me numqua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> te derelicturu, ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> contra te al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> quid vmquam dicturum, aut fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> turum; ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> permiſſurum vt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> meis ſubditis aliquid contra t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um honorem vmquam agatur Obſecro te igitur, ſuſcipe me i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeruum perpetuum: adſis mihi i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> actionibus omnibus meis, nec m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſer as in hora mortis. Amen</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:16"/>
            <head>THE PRAYER VSED TO BE ſaid by thoſe, that be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Sodality.</head>
            <p>BLESSED Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Mother of God, N.N. do this day chooſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee for my Lady, Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Aduocate; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do firmely purpoſe &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, neuer to forſake thee; nor euer to ſpeake, or do any thing againſt thee; nor at any tyme to ſuffer any thing to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:18588:17"/>thee, by thoſe that be vnder my care. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I moſt humbly beſeech thee, to receaue me into thy perpetuall ſeruice and protection; be preſent with me in all my actions; and forſake me not in the houre of death. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18588:17"/>
            <head>THE PARADISE OF DELIGHTS. OR The B. Virgins Garden of Loreto.</head>
            <div n="1" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE I. MEDITATION.</hi> Of the Venerable, and ſacred Name of the moſt B. Virgin, MARIA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ANY pious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the myſticall ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this moſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Name, <hi>Maria,</hi> haue beene
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18588:18"/>with very great reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſet down by the holy Fathers: and with no leſſe diligence learnedly colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Reuerend Father <hi>Cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> in his memorable worke <hi>Of the ſacred Virgins prayſes:</hi> which for ſo much as at this preſent ſerue to our purpoſe, we may not vnfitly reduce to three.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Maria,</hi> is as much as to ſay <hi>Stella Maris, Illuminata,</hi> or <hi>Illuminatrix,</hi> that is, Starre of the Sea, or North Starre, one that is illuminated, or giueth light to others. Secondly, <hi>Maria</hi> is <hi>amarum mare,</hi> a bitter ſea, or ſea of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And thirdly, ſhe is <hi>Dòmina</hi> Lady, or Miſtreſſo. Out of the which we may frame three point in this manner.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How fitly this ſacred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is deriued from <hi>Light;</hi> and as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18588:18"/>North-ſtar is known by the name of the Sea-ſtarre, becauſe thereby the wandering Marriners direct their courſe, the better to attaine vnto their hoped and pretended Hauen: ſo this Beautious Queen of light in the Catholike Church is placed, whoſe radiant beames of vertuous life &amp; heauenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation drawes the eyes of all thoſe who deſire to arriue at the happy Hauen of eternall bliſſe; which being fixed vpon her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable light, muſt needs eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew the dangerous ſhipwracke of this wicked world, vnles they willfully forſake the infallible di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of ſo faire a Starre, and blindly run the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt the vnhappy rockes of vtter ruyne, and euerlaſting Death.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Moreouer ſhe is ſayd to be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18588:19"/>
                  <hi>Illuminata,</hi> endued with light, and this by reaſon of the diuine knowledge of moſt high and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Miſteries, the which ſo fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely and vndoubtedly ſhe did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that not vnworthily ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to heare,<note place="margin">Luc. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Beata quae credidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi> bleſſed art thou who haſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued. And as all the beautifull ſtars do participate their borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed light which we behold from the bright ſhyning lamp of the world the Sunne, according to their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity and greatnes: euen ſo this ſacred Queene being neereſt vnto the bright Sunne of Iuſtice Chriſt Ieſus, and moſt capable of his Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall influences, and heauenly bleſſings, did participate ſo much of his diuine light, that rightly ſhe may be called <hi>Illuminata,</hi> indued with light.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18588:19"/>
               <p> Further more ſhe is ſayd to be <hi>Illuminatrix,</hi> one who giueth light vnto others: For that indeed is one of the chiefeſt effects of true vertue, as our Bleſſed Sauiour not obſcurel ye did inſinuate vnto his louing diſciples, when he ſayd, they were <hi>Lux mundi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> the light of the world, and preſently did an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexe their proper office and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Luceat lux veſtra coram homi nibus:</hi> let your light ſhine before men. This, I ſay, is a rare effect of true vertue, not only to be lightſome, yea delightſome in it ſelfe; but alſo to ſhine &amp; giue light vnto others. And this being more apparant in the B. Virgin then in all other Saints togeather, I think none will deny, but that in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner, and that moſt fitly ſhe hath this diuine <hi>Epitheton</hi> of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18588:20"/>
                  <hi>Illuminatrix,</hi> one that giueth light vnto others.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond Etimology, or deriuation of this Bleſſed Name <hi>Maria,</hi> is <hi>amarum mare,</hi> a bitter ſea, or ſea of bitter nes, which well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the ſorrowfull eſtate of the B Virgin, in the depth of her exceſſiue griefe, that ſhe ſuffered at the foot of the Croſſe, when with watry eyes, and moſt heauy hart, ſhe did behold her louing Sone, the author of life, yea life it ſelfe wraſtling with death, euen till death: Which dolefull ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle did fill her tender hart with whole floudes of ſorrow, whoſe bitter panges (as many holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue left written to vs) did leaue her more then martyred. In which almoſt deadly agony, and ſtrong encounter with a ſea of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18588:20"/>griefe, we may behould this glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Starre, almoſt ouerclouded with the thicke miſt of grief, yet yeelding a moſt beautiful light by reaſon of her conſtant fortitude; notwithſtanding we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not chooſe but ſay,<note place="margin">Thren. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Magna est velut Mare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritio tua; quis medebitur tui?</hi> Thy Contrition or ſorrow is like vnto a ſea; who ſhall be able to comfort thee? The abundant teares of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> for his murthered <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>37.</hi> Iob. <hi>10. 1.</hi> Reg. c. <hi>20. 2.</hi> Reg. <hi>18.</hi> &amp; <hi>19.</hi> Thren. per totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> the vnceſſant griefe of <hi>Anna</hi> for her wandering Pilgrime, the harty ſighes of <hi>Ionathas</hi> for his louely <hi>Dauid,</hi> the inward throbs of <hi>Dauid</hi> for his rebellious <hi>Abſalom,</hi> the pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſobs and rufull lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Ieremias</hi> for his ſinnefull people, may well be ſhaddows (&amp; but ſhaddowes) of her griefe.</p>
               <p>O ſacred Queen, in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18588:21"/>of theſe bitters ſtormes, ſhall I yet preſume to call thee beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? Me thinkes I heare thee ſay with mourneful <hi>Noëmi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ruth. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nolite vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care me Noëmi, ſed vocate me Mara quia amaritudinibus valde repleuit me Omnipotens.</hi> Call me not <hi>Noë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi> that is to ſay <hi>beautifull,</hi> but cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me <hi>Mara,</hi> that is <hi>bitter,</hi> becauſe the Almighty hath filled me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly with bitternes.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon alſo may be why ſhe ſhould be compared to a bitter ſea. Becauſe as the Red ſea prooued moſt bitter vnto <hi>Phara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> &amp; his wicked army, miraculouſly withſtanding their paſſage, and hindring their purſuit to the great comfort &amp; ſtrengthening of the children of God, and to their own vtter ruine and deſtruction: So this B. Queene is a ſea of bitternes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18588:21"/>vnto the Diuell and his damned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pirits (figured in that obſtinate Tyrant &amp; his impious followers) who like roaring lyons, neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eaſe to perſecute the choſen and beloued Children of God, ſeeking whome they may deuoure. In whoſe ſtrong defence the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Virgin is alwayes ready at hand, whoſe only Name is moſt terrible vnto them, and for theſe reſpects, ſhe is moſt iuſtly intitled <hi>amarum mare,</hi> a bitter Sea.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Then laſtly <hi>Maria,</hi> is as much as <hi>Domina,</hi> Lady, or Miſtreſſe: &amp; with great reaſon, for indeed ſhe was euer Lady &amp; Miſtreſſe ouer all her actions, making alwayes her inward thoughts keep a moſt perfect co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord with her outward deedes; and both the one and the other directly to tend to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18588:22"/>honour and glory of God, the true and chiefeſt ſcope of all her vertuous endeauours.</p>
               <p>Beſides, ſhe may be ſayd to be <hi>Domina,</hi> a Lady, a powerfull Princeſſe, or mighty Empreſſe, by reaſon of the great power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſhe hath with her ſweet Sonne, to help and ſuccour ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as moſt deuoutly S. <hi>Bernard</hi> doth acknowledg,<note place="margin">Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ſer. in Apo. c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> when he ſayth <hi>Amplectamur Mariae veſtigia &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotiſsima ſupplicatione beatis illius pedibus prouoluamur: teneamus eam, nec dimittamus donec bene dixerit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, potens eſt enim.</hi> Let vs imbrace the ſacred footſtepps of Bleſſed Mary, and with moſt deuout ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, let vs fall at her bleſſed feet, let vs take hold on her, and neuer let go, vntill ſhe vouchſafe to grace vs with her bleſſing, for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18588:22"/>ſhe is powerfull.</p>
               <p>Thus hauing ſomewhat diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouered the hidden treaſure wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted in this happy Name of <hi>Mary;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The fruit of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> followeth that we ſtirr vp our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſires and inflame our harts with moſt feruerous deuotion and true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oue towardes ſo beautifull a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly. What ſoule in danger of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all ſhip wracke, beaten with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough billowes of ſinne, &amp; threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed with the ſurging waues of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant death, would not open his deafe eares and hearing the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable voyce of S. <hi>Bernard</hi> giue attentiue eare, whileſt he ſayth, <hi>Reſpice ſtellam, voca Mariam,</hi> looke vp man that art in perill, view this beautifull Star, call vpon the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Name of <hi>Mary.</hi> What man ſo wretched, who hauing crucifyed her only Sonne by his manifold
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18588:23"/>ſinnes &amp; grieuous offences, would not run to the foot of the Croſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where this ſorrowfull Mother ſtandeth, and weep floods of tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for his miſdemeanour, and by he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> powerfull interceſſion obtay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> forgiuenes of them. What ſinful wight in diſtreſſe and miſery would not fly vnto ſo powerfull Lady, to obtaine new ſtrength <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greater forces whereby to maſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his vnbridled appetits, and oue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come his diſordered paſſions? Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally who would not be ſerua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſo mighty a Princeſſe? who would not be ſuppliant to ſo lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a Mother, and wholy deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſo beautifull a Queene?</p>
               <p>Heerupon I wil in moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner deſire the gloriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Queen of heauen,<note place="margin">The Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquium</note> that hencefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by her motherly help I may ſo kee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18588:23"/>myne eyes fixed vpon the bright <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eames of her ſhining vertue, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vtterly hate all workes of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, and ſo drown my ſoule in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owing ſtreams of deuotion, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may waſh away al the ſtaynes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y former offences, and neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore offend Almighty God: yea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at I may alwayes fly vnder her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>otection, &amp; that ſhe wil vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fe to guard and defend me; <hi>Sub <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um praeſidium confugimus ſancta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ei genitrix,</hi> vnder thy protection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e flye, O holy Mother of God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o conclude this Meditation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t vs with a firme and reſolute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rpoſe dedicate our ſelues who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vnto her, in all our neceſſityes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue confident recourſe vnto her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d to the beſt of our powers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>itate her excellent heroical ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, as the moſt true token of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18588:24"/>our loue, and moſt louely pledge of our endles friendſhip. For the better obteyning whereof, let v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heere deuoutly recite the <hi>Salu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Regina,</hi> or <hi>Aue Maris Stella</hi> which in this place is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE II. MEDITATION</hi> Of the rare ſanctity of the Bleſſed Virgin.</head>
               <p>THREE famous workes w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> read to haue beene moſt curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly accompliſhed by the wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> King <hi>Salomon</hi> in the old Law which if we conſider as types an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> figures of what our true <hi>Salomon</hi> Chriſt Ieſus did afterward fullfil in his bleſſed Mother, they wil help vs ſomewhat to declare th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18588:24"/>vnſpeakable greatnes of the rare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anctity of the holy mother of God which is indeed ſo far beyond all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umane reach, as the wits &amp; beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nderſtandings muſt be forced with S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to cry out, <hi>Quid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icam de te paupere ingenie?</hi> What can be ſayd of thee by the weake wit of man? Where the high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of learned S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> came ſhort; vvhere the golden eloquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of fluent S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vvas not inough; vvhere the graue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ences of renovvned S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raue pardon; vvhere the famous workes of learned S. <hi>Hierome</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe their weaknes; the piercing eye of enlightned <hi>S. Anſelme</hi> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eleth; the hony-flowing ſtile of Holy S. <hi>Bernard</hi> is dryed vp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he deuout hart of ſeraphicall S. <hi>Bonauenture</hi> is conſumed; finally
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18588:25"/>where al the whole troope of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Writters doe acknowledge themſelues vnable to declare thy vnſpeakable prayſe, I muſt needs ſay with S. <hi>Augustine:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. <hi>18.</hi> de San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis.</note> 
                  <hi>Accipite ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quaſcum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> exiles, quaſcum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> meritis tuis impares, gratiarum acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes,</hi> accept of theſe how euer ſo ſlender prayſes, how euer ſo vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, vnto thy worthy merits.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt worke of this fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named King, regiſtred in holy Writ,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 1.6.</note> is the building of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which both for great coſt and excellent workmanſhip may well be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Mirrour of all Ages, an earthly Heauen, where God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe choſe to dwell, and of the which we read, <hi>Nihil erat qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> non auro tegeretur,</hi> there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that was not couered with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18588:25"/>gold. If now we turne our eyes to the ſacred Temple of the Sonne of God, to the diuine Tabernacle of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſecret clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet of the bleſſed Trinity, the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> we ſhal find her a worke beyond all admiration; wrought by the eternall Wiſedom of Almighty God; adorned with all kind of vertue; enriched with aboundance of diuine grace, and prepared as an vnſpotted veyle, wherein God himſelfe ſhould be inwrapped, that ſo indeed ſhe might become the ſacred Temple of God, ſo enlightned with grace, ſo inflamed with Charity, that al the world might ſee &amp; beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that <hi>Nihil erat quod non aur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tegeretur,</hi> there was nothing in her, that was not couered with golden Charity. Neither was the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18588:26"/>famous Temple of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo frequented as is this Holy Temple of God, becauſe as S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>omnibus ſinum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordiae aperit, vt de plenitudine eius accipiant vniuerſi:</hi> She layeth open her mercifull breaſt vnto all, that of her great aboundance eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one may take part.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond worke of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration recorded in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we find to be a ſtately Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace that King <hi>Salomon</hi> erected for his owne vſe. And this was fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by him, and brought to full perfection in thirteen yeares. But Wiſedome it ſelfe built the houſe of which we heere ſpeake, and for himſelfe, <hi>Sapientia aedificauit ſibi domum,</hi> Wiſedome built himſelfe a houſe, of which the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſpake when he ſayd: <hi>Erit praepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18588:26"/>mons domus Domini in vertice nontium:</hi> There ſhall be a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain prepared for the houſe of our Lord in the top of Mountaynes. Which words S. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great expoundeth of the Bleſſed Virgin thus: <hi>An non mons ſublimis Maria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">in Reg. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uae vt conceptionem aeterni verbi at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ingeret, meritorum vertice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad ſolium Deitatis erexit:</hi> Is not this Virgin a high &amp; lofty mountayn, who to reach to the Conception of the Sonne of God ſhe rayſed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eight of her merits aboue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uirs of Angels vnto the thron of God. And as by the mountaine is ſignifyed <hi>Perfection,</hi> ſhe being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in the top of mountaynes, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth vs to vnderſtand of how great perfection and rare ſanctity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he was, &amp; is aboue al other Saints and Angels: and all this the diuin
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18588:27"/>Wiſedome had brought to paſſe in the ſpace of thirteene yeares; for ſhe was not full fourteene, when ſhe was choſen the Mother of God.</p>
               <p>Behold then, O my ſoule, this ſtately Pallace, aſcend this holy mountaine, admire the diuine workemanſhip of all, and euery part of this famous building, and thou wilt be forced to ſay <hi>Digit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Dei est hic,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> this worke could only be done by the finger of God.</p>
               <p>The third worke of fame mentioned in Holy Writ, was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtately Throne, which King <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> built for himſelfe, &amp; where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he gloryed very much, of which the holy Scripture auerreth: <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſt factum tale opus in vniuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> regnis:</hi> The like peece of work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was not made in the vvorld: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18588:27"/>was of Iuory, couered with the beſt gold; it was beſet with prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cely Lyons in diuers places, and there were ſix ſteps to aſcend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. By the Iuory Throne co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered with beaten gold is ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Bleſſed Virgin, by reaſon of her chaſt purity, and the moſt beautifull luſtre of her golden Charity. The ſix ſtepps ſignify <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>x vertuous acts, by which we muſt aſcend into the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ins fauour, ſignifyed by theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etters of her venerable Name <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irjám,</hi> for <hi>Sochath,</hi> the Hebrew word. The ſtepps be theſe; <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nimity, Inuocation, Reuerence, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itation, Affection,</hi> and <hi>Memory</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. <hi>Magnanimity</hi> bringeth forth a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me &amp; conſtant <hi>Reſolution</hi> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uly hers. <hi>Inuocation,</hi> calleth vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r for ayde and ſuccour, for the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18588:28"/>better performance of this good purpoſe. <hi>Reuerence</hi> cauſeth a deſire of <hi>Imitation. Imitation</hi> breeds loue and affection. <hi>Affection</hi> keepes a perpetuall memory of what we loue: &amp; <hi>Memory</hi> is both a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aduiſer of what we haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and a certaine Note-booke of what we haue receaued.</p>
               <p>Theſe be the ſhaddows which may in ſome ſort giue vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the admirable ſanctity of the euer Bleſſed Queen of Angels and holy Mother of ſinners. For greater was the Sanctity of this excellent Virgin, then the ſanctity of all Saints and Angells, iointl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conceaued, as both Fathers, and Deuines do auerre. <hi>Ceteris per par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Mariae autem ſe infudit tota gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae plenitudo,</hi> ſayth <hi>S Hierome:</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other Saints grace was giuen by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18588:28"/>parts, but to this ſacred Queene, all fullnes of grace was at once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed. And therefore moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily ſhe was ſaluted by the Angel when he brought his heauenly Embaſſage <hi>Gratia plena,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> full of grace, that of her fullnes (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſayd out of S. <hi>Bernard</hi>) we might all participate.</p>
               <p>Hauing thus by theſe three conſiderations grafted in our harts and minds the vnſpeakable great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of her imcomparable ſanctity and fullnes of grace, it reſteth that as little children &amp; tender Infants we haue recourſe vnto her, who is louing, and therfore will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vs; who is our Mother, and therefore cannot be forgetfull of her poore diſtreſſed children, who with true deuotion ſeeke her. Let vs therefore cry, and call, <hi>Sancta
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18588:29"/>Maria ora pro nobis,</hi> Holy Mary pray for vs. <hi>Monſtra te eſſe Matrem,</hi> ſhew thy ſelfe a Mother. And the better to incline her louing hart, that ſhe may ſhew her ſelfe a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Mother, let vs ſhew our ſelues true &amp; obedient children, giuing attentiue eare vnto the diuine ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and healthfull counſell of S. <hi>Peter: Quaſi modo geniti infantes rationabiles, ſine dolo, lac concupiſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.</hi> As new borne children reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, without deceipt, deſire yee milke: not ſweet alluring milke of vayne pleaſure &amp; worldly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nityes, but the true nouriſhing milke of a pure &amp; vnſpotted life; the delightſome milke of deuout loue to the B. Virgin, in which we may increaſe vnto eternall happines.</p>
               <p>All haile, O ſacred Virgin,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18588:29"/>full of grace the Mirrour of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> and patterne of all perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Behould I moſt vnworthy of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l thy Children do heer proſtrate my ſelfe at thy feet, deſiring from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he bottome of my hart that thou wilt vouchſafe to take me vnder thy protection, and with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undance of thy gracious fauours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o to enrich my needy ſoule, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may be gratefull vnto thy belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Sonne, &amp; pleaſing vnto thee. And being honored with ſo great and high a Title as to be called <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hyne,</hi> I may endeauour to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmoſt of my power ſo to behaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſelfe, that I may in all my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns ſhevv my ſelfe a true child of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch a Mother. Amen. <hi>Salue Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>na.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18588:30"/>
               <head>THE III. MEDITATION. <hi>Sancta Dei genitrix ora pro nobis.</hi> Holy Mother of God, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>THIS moſt excellent Title of Mother of God is giuen to the Bleſſed Virgin, by the holy Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts in diuers places. S. <hi>Matthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> recounting the genealogy of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, deriueth it from <hi>Abraham,</hi> and bringeth it to <hi>S. Ioſeph,</hi> Spouſe of the Bleſſed Virgin, <hi>De qua na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt Ieſus, qui v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>catur Chriſtus;</hi> of whome was borne Ieſus who is called Chriſt. S <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaking of the wedding in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee,</hi> ſayth: <hi>Erat mater Ieſu ibi,</hi> The Mother of Ieſus was there. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:18588:30"/>at the death of our Bleſſed Sauiour making mention of her conſtant fortitude at the foot of the Croſſe writeth: <hi>Stabat iuxta Crucem Ieſu Mater eius:</hi> Ieſus his Mother ſtood at the foot of the Croſſe. In the Acts of the Apoſtles, S <hi>Luke</hi> alſo honoureth her with the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned title of the <hi>Mother of God,</hi> all which being inuincible teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyes need no further proofe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt then, I wil conſider how this excellent title of <hi>Mother of God,</hi> is the chiefe ground &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all her rare, and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar prerogatiues. Why ſhould this heauenly Queen be called, and be both Mother &amp; Virgin? Becauſe ſo it was fit for the B. Mother of God. Wherefore preſerued from all ſpot, both of actuall and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne? Becauſe ſhe was the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:18588:31"/>Mother of God. Why repleniſhed with grace aboue all other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? For the ſame reaſon that ſhe was Mother of God. Why more Holy then all Saints &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells togeather? Becauſe ſuch ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity was agreable to the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned title of Mother of God. She was elected the deuine Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the moſt Higheſt, <hi>Et ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficauit Tabernaculum ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altiſsimus,</hi> &amp; thus he ſanctifyed his holy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle. This moſt noble Title therefore being giuen her, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her profound humility, the ground of all vertues, was the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of all the reſt her ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar fauours.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But to diue a litle further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to botomles depth of this match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Title; let vs conſider the greatnes therof. If there could be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18588:31"/>found ſome noble Lady on earth, whoſe Father ſhould excell all the world in power, riches and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; whoſe Sonne did go beyond all creatures in wiſedome wealth, and nobility; and laſtly whoſe Spouſe did equall them both in all noble acts and veriuous procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings: if ſuch a Lady could be found for her ſingular vertues and rare qualityes, worthy to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged of ſuch a Father, to be honoured by ſuch a Sonne, and to be beloued of ſuch a Spouſe; what titles could this gracious Queene be honoured with, but ſuch as both by Father, Sonne, &amp; Spouſe muſt needs be excellent? Conſider then the euer Bleſſed &amp; moſt happy Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto Almighty God, Mother to his only Sonne, and Eſpouſed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18588:32"/>to the Holy Ghoſt; who for her profound humility, Angelicall chaſtity, moſt burning Charity, and the reſt of her admirable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, is moſt worthily and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued of them all. And ſhall we not thinke they would honour her with ſuch a title, as might both anſwere the greatnes of them that gaue it, and be moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to her that ſhould receaue it? Yea doubtleſſe. And vvhat title could this be but, <hi>Sancta Dei Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix,</hi> Holy Mother of God, <hi>Mater Ieſu,</hi> Mother of Ieſus.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I will then conſider the great dignity of this moſt noble Title. For the better vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we may contemplate how in the Eternal Wiſedome of God the Father, the ſecond perſon of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Trinity, was from all Eternity
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18588:32"/>borne of his Father without a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and at the decreed tyme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be borne of a Mother with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Father, he made choiſe of the Bleſſed Virgin, which was the greateſt dignity which any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could be exalted vnto; as this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acred Queene did moſt humbly acknowledge and prayſe God for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſame, in her diuine Canticle, when ſhe did alſo propheſy how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or his cauſe all people ſhould call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er <hi>Bleſſed: Ecce enim ex hoc beatam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e dicent omnes generationes:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from henceforth all genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall call me Bleſſed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt worthily this honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble title is placed in the beginning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> her Letanyes, as the chiefe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ound of all the reſt of her noble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deuout appellations. This I ſay in the beginning, as the greateſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18588:33"/>and moſt worthy to be engrafted in the harts of all ſuch as deſire to come vnto her, for the ſweet milk of true &amp; cordiall deuotion. And as little Infants neuer ceaſe crying and calling after their Mothers, or Nurſes, vntill they ſee them; and neuer content vntill they come to ſucke the full duggs, and imbrace the paps from whence they draw their ſuſtenance: So ought we to cry after this our louing Mother, and thinke our ſelues and ſoules robbed vntill we both find her, &amp; taſt the ſweet milke of deuotion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpake, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> imagining himſelfe betweene th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſacred wounds of Chriſt, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> full duggs of the B. Virgin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſayd: <hi>hinc paſcor à vulnere, hinc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ab vbere.</hi> On the one ſide I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fed with the precious bloud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18588:33"/>Chriſt, on the other with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion-flowing teats of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin; of which two dainties <hi>S. Bonauenture</hi> alſo gloryed, and ſayd he made himſelf a moſt ſweet potion.</p>
               <p>O euer Bleſſed,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> and moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Mother of God, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo great a Title, and high dignity, doſt not diſdaine to be the Mother of ſinners; vouchſafe to caſt thy humble eye vpon a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate and forſaken Orphane, who cryeth with the Kingly Prophet: <hi>Tibi derelictus est pauper; orphano tu es adiutrix:</hi> Vnto thee the poore is left, and thou wilt be a help vnto the Orphane: <hi>Ad te ſuſpiramus ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes &amp; flentesin hac lachrymarum valle. Eia ergo aduocata noſtra, illos tuos miſericordes oculos ad nos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte.</hi> Vnto thee, O ſacred Queen
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18588:34"/>we crye, groaning and lamenting in this vale of miſeryes. Come therfore, O moſt Bleſſed aduocate turne thy mercifull eyes towards vs, heare our humble pititions, <hi>Sancta Dei genitrix ora pro nobis:</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mother of God pray for vs, that we may eſcape the manifold dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers of this wicked life; that we may follow thy diuine and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble footſteps; that we may not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in word and hart acknowledge thee the Mother of God, but alſo come to behould thy glorious Crowne, which thou haſt recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, anſwerable to ſo worthy a Title and ſo great a dignity. And that ſo we may reioyce with thee for all eternity, Amen. <hi>Salue Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gina &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="meditation">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:18588:34"/>
               <head>THE IIII. MEDITATION. <hi>Sancta Virgo Virginum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Holy Virgin of Virgins, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>CONCERNING this <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theton,</hi> we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider three principal points. Firſt the dignity of Virginity. Secondly why the Bleſſed Virgin, is called <hi>Virgo Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginum,</hi> Virgin of Virgins. Laſtly of what eſteeme virginity is with God, and our B. Lady.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt conſideration of the excellency of Virginity, we find expreſſed &amp; counſelled by Chriſt, when in the myſticall parable of the three kindes of Eunuches,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt, ſayth he, are ſuch as haue made themſelues chaſt, for the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18588:35"/>kingdom of heauen: and to ſhew the difficulty in attaining to this excellent vertue,<note place="margin">Matt. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> he addeth, <hi>Qui poteſt capere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>capiat:</hi> he that can reach vnto it, let him imbrace and follow it. The like proofe we haue of the dignity of virginall chaſtity, out of another parable, where Chriſt comparing his holy Church to a good land, whereof one part yealdeth fruit thirty fold,<note place="margin">Cypr. de hab. virg. Hier. l. <hi>1.</hi> in Iou. Auguſt. de ſancta virg. c. <hi>44.</hi> &amp; <hi>45.</hi>
                  </note> another ſixty, and ſome an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred: vnderſtanding heereby, as ſome Fathers expound, the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity of honeſt wiues, deuout wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and vertuous Virgins; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vvhich, as the chiefeſt, Virginity bringeth forth an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold. S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolleth the quiet condition of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall life,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note> becauſe as it is more free from troubles and vexations
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18588:35"/>of the fleſh, ſo it is an eſtate more ſequeſtred from earthly pleaſures, and therefore more fit for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God.</p>
               <p>Moreouer the excellency of this celeſtiall gift may be gathered out of the common and continual practiſe of the Church, and the high eſteeme the holy Fathers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had of this ſo pretious a iewel. S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calleth it <hi>Principalis vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Virg.</note> the chiefeſt vertue, adding that no vvit is able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the dignity thereof, becauſe it exceeds the bondes of Nature, pierceth the clouds, paſſeth aboue the Stars, goeth beyond the quires of Angels, and taketh the Sonne of God for Spouſe.<note place="margin">De diſc. &amp; habit. Virg.</note> S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> calleth virginity, the flowre of the Church, the grace, and ornament of ſpirituall fauour, the liuely i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18588:36"/>of our Sauiour, deciphring his ſanctity, and the more illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous portion of the Church and flock of Chriſt. I omit others, for by theſe we may ſufficiently vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the excellency &amp; dignity of virginity conſidered in it ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider why, &amp; with how great reaſon the B. Mother of God is called <hi>Virgin of Virgins.</hi> Where we may contemplate, how this ſacred Queene was the firſt, that euer offered her virginity to God by Holy Vow; and this either in the Temple at her Preſentation being of three years of age, where ſhe was brought vp vntil by diuin ordination ſhe was eſpouſed to S. <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> or, as ſome thinke, ſhe made this laudable vow (being preuented with the vſe of reaſon) in her Mothers wombe. Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18588:36"/>it was all with vniforme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent agree that in this ſhe was the firſt, and therfore, moſt worthily intitled the <hi>Virgin of Virgins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, ſhe may moſt iuſtly be named <hi>Virgin of Virgins,</hi> becauſe in her vnſpotted life ſhe was the moſt perfect modell of all vertues, the moſt exact patterne of virginity, &amp; the moſt liuely example for all Virgins, whereby to frame their actions, and ſome their liues, as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> witneſſeth: <hi>Sit vobis</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>tamquam in imagine deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cripta virginitas, vita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Beatae Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambr. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Virg.</note> 
                  <hi>de qua velut in ſpeculo refulget ſpecies Caſtitatis, &amp; forma virtutis.</hi> Let the virginity, and life of the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> be vnto you as it were engrauen in an image, from which as in a lookinglaſſe the beames of Chaſtity, and the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18588:37"/>forme of vertue do yeald a moſt beautifull luſtre. For heere you ſhall find, both what to fly, and what to follow. And furthermore to ſtir vp in our harts an earneſt deſire to learne of ſuch a Miſtreſſe to follow ſuch a guide, and leuell our liues to ſuch a rule, he ſetteth forth her vertue and nobility as followeth: <hi>Primus diſcendi ardor, nobilitas eſt magiſtri,</hi> the firſt and chiefeſt motiue of the deſyre of learning, is the nobility of the maiſter: then further; <hi>Quid nobiliùs Dei matre, quid ſplendidiùs ea quam ſplendor elegit?</hi> What more noble then the Mother of God, what more bright then ſhe whome brightnes hath elected and choſen for his Mother? She therefore for nobility deſerues the Title of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, and for her bright ſhining
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18588:37"/>vertue worthy the moſt exact pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of all perfection.</p>
               <p>Againe ſhe may be ſayd to be the <hi>Virgin of Virgins,</hi> becauſe vnto the honour of her virginity was ioyned the fruitfulneſſe of a Mother, neuer the like heard of before, neuer the like hoped for heereafter: <hi>Virgo perpetua, mater &amp; Virgo</hi> (ſayth <hi>S. Hierome</hi>) a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Virgin and Mother, or Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin-Mother, and therfore <hi>Mother of Virgins,</hi> and <hi>Virgin of Virgins.</hi> This is the Eaſterne gate (as <hi>S. Hierom</hi> expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth) alwayes ſhut, alwayes ſhining, mentioned by the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> graced with the Title of Mother, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out detriment or hurt of her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted virginity, alwayes remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Virgin: therfore we ought to call vpon her, and earneſtly to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18588:38"/>cry vnto her, <hi>Sancta virgo Virginu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ora pro nobis.</hi> Holy Virgin of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, pray for vs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third point may be to conſider, how gratefull this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is in the ſight of God, and how pleaſing vnto the Bleſſed Virgin. So highly eſteemed in the ſight of God, that being to effect one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous work, that ſhould be the wonder of the world, that is, to wrap himſelfe in the ſlender veyle of our humanity, &amp; become man amongſt men; he would not take that mantle, but of a Virgin, and a Virgin dedicated vnto himſelfe by a perpetuall vow of chaſtity: <hi>Virginitate placuit, Humilitate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Bernard:</hi> By virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhe ſeemed pleaſing vnto him, and by Humility ſhe became his Mother, or (as S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18588:38"/>by Chaſtity. This is that Altar of Perfumes, called <hi>Altare Thymia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis,</hi> ſo pleaſing vnto God. This is that dainty Roſe of <hi>Saron</hi> ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging from the pricky thornes of mortification: this that beautifull lylly of the humble vallies, which admitteth not the leaſt touch or ſtain: it is that floriſhing flower of the field, which being roted in the B. virgin, hath now ſprouted forth ſo many branches, that we may wel ſee and ſay, <hi>Flores apparuerunt in terra nosstra:</hi> Flowers haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in our Land; and being virginall flowers, and flowers of virginity, <hi>Adducentur Regi virgines poſt eam:</hi> After her, troops of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens ſhall be brought to the King of Kinges, to Chriſt the true Spouſe of holy Virgins. For, <hi>Ole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um effuſum nomen tuum ideo Adoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centulae
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18588:39"/>dilexerunt te.</hi> Thy name, O Lord, is oyle powred out, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore young virgins loue thee, and following thy diuine ſteps they cry: <hi>In odorem vnguentorum tuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> curremus:</hi> We will runne after the ſweet ſmell of thy pretious oynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>Virginity muſt alſo be moſt pleaſing to the B. Virgin: for ſhe knowing beſt the valew of ſuch dainty flowers, and conſidering how much they are eſteemed by her ſweet Sonne, muſt needs haue a particuler loue therto, and a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar care therof that ſuch choice flowers be not defiled, or tramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on by incurſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of bruit beaſts. And as one that is the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſome holy &amp; Religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, hath a moſt diligent care both to defend &amp; aduance his religious
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18588:39"/>Inſtitute, and taketh great delight in the increaſe and progreſſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: ſo the B. Virgin being the firſt that euer found out this Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call life, the firſt that layd the ground and foundation of vowed Chaſtity, the firſt that diſplayd the banner, vnder which all chaſt virgins ought manfully to fight, &amp; vnder which ſo many haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready winne the goale, gotten the victory, and worne the Crowne: She, I ſay, muſt needs take great delight in the groth of theſe ſo faire flowers of her louing Sonne, as he takes great content in gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of them. Witnes thoſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull flowers of virginity &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant pillars of renowned Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, tranſplanted by our Sauiours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and from this garden of miſery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto the heauenly place of Paradiſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18588:40"/>
                  <hi>S. Catherine,</hi> S. <hi>Agatha,</hi> S. <hi>Lucy,</hi> S. <hi>Agnes,</hi> S. <hi>Cecily,</hi> S. <hi>Winifride,</hi> and thouſands more in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, who rather made choice to looſe their liues, then liue to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of ſo rare a Iewel, and with the vnſpoted <hi>Ermyn</hi> ſeemed rather to dye then be defiled.</p>
               <p>And thus hauing viewed the excellency of Virginity in it ſelfe, the eſteeme it hath in the ſight of God, the prize it beares vvith the Bleſſed Virgin: and conſidering hovv truly ſhe is <hi>Virgin of Virgins;</hi> let vs ſtir vp in our ſelues a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend loue vnto this excellent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and deſire this Virgin of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to pray for vs, that we may euery one in his eſtate, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his calling imitate this glorious Virgin, in keeping our ſoules and bodyes as the chaſt veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18588:40"/>and choſen tabernacles of the Holy Ghoſt, bringing forth fruit, ſome thirty, ſome ſixty, and ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n hundred fold, whereby we ſhall be moſt pleaſing to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oued of the B. Virgin, and ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the happy number of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elect band, of ſo many thouſands of moſt holy &amp; vnſpotted virgins whoſe priuiledge is to follow the Lambe whereſouer, and whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he goeth: to which effect let vs ſay, <hi>Aue Maris ſtella &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="meditation">
               <head>THE V. MEDITATION. <hi>Mater Chriſti, ora pro nobis.</hi> Mother of Chriſt, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>HAVING contemplated the excellent dignity of the Holy Mother of God, let vs now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18588:41"/>her as <hi>Mother of Chriſt,</hi> which although it be the ſame in effect, yet heere we will ponder ſome particuler points, as it were deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from this word <hi>Chriſt,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may the better appeare what dignity hath redounded to the B. Virgin by being called <hi>Mother of Christ.</hi> Chriſt therfore, is as much to ſay, as <hi>Annointed,</hi> becauſe he was indeed the annointed of his Father, <hi>Vnxit te Deus, Deus tuus,</hi> O God, thy God hath annointed thee, and that <hi>Oleo laetitiae prae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortibus tuis,</hi> with oyle of gladnes aboue thy fellowes. By which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin vnction is ſignifyed the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of heauenly grace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſacred Humanity of Chriſt was beautifyed aboue al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Prieſts, Prophets and Kings
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18588:41"/>are wont to be annoynted, to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnify the particuler grace which they haue giuen them to perform their functions: and Chriſt Ieſus being both Prieſt, Prophet, and King, ought by al titles to be <hi>Chriſt</hi> that is <hi>Annoynted,</hi> ſo that by Chriſt we vnderſtand as it were the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fountain of all graces, from whoſe fullnes we al receaue to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy our wants. Now if we ſeeke the head of this diuine fountaine, we ſhal find it hath one beginning in heauen from all eternity of his Father, another on earth <hi>in fine temporum,</hi> towards the end of the world,<note place="margin">Homo in fine tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum.</note> when being made Man he came to pay the ranſome of our ſinnes, and that is his bleſſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, heere iuſtly intitled <hi>Mater Chriſti,</hi> Mother of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Let vs now conſider foure
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18588:42"/>propertyes of oyle, which will in ſome ſort declare vnto vs the wonderfull effects of this diuine oyle, whereby the greatnes of the benefit we haue receaued of the B. Virgin (who was Mother vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Annoynted Sonne of God, and brought him into this world among vs) may appeare the more.</p>
               <p>The firſt property of Oyle is to feed vs, and this S. <hi>Bernard</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and experience teacheth, &amp; Chriſt is he who is our true food, without whom no ſoule can liue; for vnles we eate his fleſh, and drink his bloud, we cannot auoyd eternall death. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the deſert were cloyed with the heauenly <hi>Manna,</hi> and ſayd, they vvere vveary of ſo light meates; therefore by the povverfull hand of Almighty God they vvere ſoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18588:42"/>chaſtized with fiery Serpents, the ſtinging wherof could not be cured, but by the beholding of the brazen ſerpent: So if we be cloyed with this diuine food, vvhich the Bleſſed Virgin hath brought vnto vs; what can we expect but the annoyance and byting of fiery ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that is of vnruly paſſions, diſordered, and diſordinate luſtes of the fleſh, neuer ceaſing to afflict vs vntil we caſt our eyes vpon our B. Sauiour nayled to the Croſſe, ſigured in the brazen ſerpent; vvhich if we do vvith true deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, firme fayth, and harty repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of our ſinnes, we ſhall be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, and our ſoule ſhall find it ſelfe refreſhed vvith the oyle of glade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es; for as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſayth: <hi>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccato dolet, &amp; de dolore gaudet,</hi> a ſinner grieueth for the ſinne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18588:43"/>&amp; reioyceth that he is ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull for it.</p>
               <p>The ſecond property gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the ſame <hi>S. Bernard</hi> is, that it giueth light: and as Chriſt himſelfe auerreth, he is the light of the world, <hi>Lux ſum mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di:</hi> I am the light of the world: therfore who ſoeuer findeth himſelfe oppreſſed with the darke cloudes of dull ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, let him haue recourſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this diuine lampe of burning oyle; and let him with the blind man call vpon him and ſay, <hi>Lord haue mercy on me:</hi> &amp; if moſt boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Ieſus ſhal demand what thou wouldſt haue? Thou ſhalt anſwere <hi>Lord, that I may ſee light.</hi> What light? The light of thy celeſtiall doctrine, of thy heauenly grace, of thy eternall glory.</p>
               <p>Another property of oyle is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18588:43"/>to cure wounds, as the ſame Holy Saint recordeth, of which we haue an euident proofe out of the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the miſerable man, who deſcending from <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Hierico,</hi> fell into the handes of theeues, &amp; being ſore wounded, was cured by oyle and wine. The precious bloud of Chriſt, is the medicinable oyle powred forth for the cure of our ſoules, &amp; ſalue of our ſoars; this muſt be the only remedy of our bleeding wounds.</p>
               <p>The laſt property of oyle is (as S. <hi>Gregory</hi> writeth) to ſwim aboue all other liquors, which is the true effect of the grace of Chriſt, to make them who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued therewith to ſwim aboue al waters of tribulation; and though for a tyme they may ſeeme to be caſt down, becauſe we ſee them
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18588:44"/>encountred with ſo many changes and chances; yet they will come vp to their naturall place againe, &amp; like the flouriſhing palme grow the faſter vnder the greateſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, for that is to floriſh like the palme, as the Kingly Prophet wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>Iuſtus vt palma florebit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the foure excellent propertyes of oyle which do ſhew vnto vs the admirable cures that Chriſt by his diuine grace vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in our ſoules. And the Bleſſed Virgin being called <hi>Mother of Chriſt,</hi> if we vvant food to our ſoules, we muſt call to her, that ſhe would vouchſafe to pray vnto her moſt louing Sonne to feed vs. If we be deſtitute of light, that ſhe vvould intreate him to enlighten vs. If we be wounded, that ſhe would deſire him to cure vs. If we
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18588:44"/>be oppreſſed &amp; ready to be drovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the depth of miſery, that ſhe vvould by her Motherly interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion pray him to releeue vs vvith his mercy, that we faile not in his cauſe, but like vnto oyle, alwayes ſtriue to aſcend, that ſo we may ſhew our ſelues to haue participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that diuine oyle Chriſt, vnto whoſe euer Bleſſed Mother we muſt haue recourſe, ſaying: <hi>Mater Christi ora pro nobis,</hi> Mother of Chriſt pray for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="meditation">
               <head>THE VI. MEDITATION. <hi>Mater diuinae gratiae, ora pro nobis.</hi> Mother of diuine grace, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>THIS Diuine Tile may be giuen to the Bleſſed Virgin
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18588:45"/>for three reaſons, which yeald vs three deuout points of Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt reaſon why ſhe is called <hi>Mother of diuine grace,</hi> is, becauſe ſhe is the mother of Chriſt who is the author of all graces, and fauours, and repleniſhed with ſuch aboundance of grace, that not vnfitly he may be called <hi>Grace</hi> it ſelfe, whoſe Bleſſed Mother was the Queene of Angells, of whom we ſpeake, and therefore moſt rightly intitled <hi>Mother of Diuine grace.</hi> For if we conſider the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold benefits which we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued from our Sauiour by his comming amongſt vs, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of grace we may draw from the Holy Sacraments, which he hath left as fountaines co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally flowing like the ſeauen-hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18588:45"/>
                  <hi>Nilus,</hi> to which we may run at our pleaſure, to refreſh our nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and thirſty ſoules: Theſe things Iſay, conſidered, &amp; how he choſe the Bleſſed Virgin to be the long deſired ſhip, that could bring vs in, to our hauen at once ſuch a precious Iewel, as might not only ſupply al our wants, but alſo make vs exceeding rich; we may with great reaſon ſay, <hi>Mother of diuine grace, pray for vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond reaſon of this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Title is, becauſe of the great aboundance of ſpirituall graces, wherewith this ſacred Queen was endowed, as partly we haue ſayd in the former Meditations, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall more playnely appeare. She was ſaluted by the heauenly Embaſſadour <hi>Gratia plena,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> or as the Greeke word imports <hi>Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18588:46"/>gracious,</hi> becauſe by reaſon of her great merits, ſhe was aboue all creatures pleaſing vnto God, and for this great aboundance of grace produced in her bleſſed ſoule, partly, by the gift of God, and partly by her owne cooperating thereto, ſhe may fitly be called <hi>Mother of Diuine grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if we confider with at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention how this grace did incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſe in the Bleſſed Virgin, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chooſe, but acknowledge her to be the <hi>Mother of diuine grace.</hi> For as many Deuines affirme, the B. Virgin by euery act doubled the grace ſhe had before receaued and this for the ſpace of all her life which was 72. yeares (as the beſt Writers do proue) vvhereby in the end of her life the grace wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe was indued, vvas almoſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18588:46"/>infinite, &amp; far ſurpaſſeth the weak reach of humane reaſon to vnfold. How rightly then do vve call her, <hi>Mother of diuine grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The third reaſon of this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation is, becauſe ſhe is a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Aduocate for vs vnto her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Sonne, &amp; doth by her holy interceſſion obtaine grace &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for our ſins. For as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> deuoutly writeth, <hi>Quidquid nos habere voluit, id per Mariam tranſire diſpoſuit:</hi> Whatſoeuer God would haue vs to receaue, that vvould he haue to paſſe through the handes of the Bleſſed Virgin. And for this cauſe ſhe is ſayd to be as it vvere the <hi>Necke,</hi> &amp; <hi>Throat</hi> of the Church and Chriſt the <hi>Head.</hi> And as all that maintaynes the body, paſſeth from the head through the Throat to the chiefe parts of the body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:18588:47"/>the which it is duely diſtributed to all the reſt of the members: ſo all that commeth from Chriſt vnto his Spouſe the Church, he will haue to paſſe through the ſacred handes of the Bleſſed Virgin, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the whole body, &amp; euery mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Holy Church: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſay, <hi>Mater diuinae gratiae, ora pro nobis,</hi> Mother of diuine grace pray for vs.</p>
               <p>O happy Mother of diuine grace,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> who by thy profound hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, vnſpotted chaſtity, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable charity, and the reſt of thy excellent vertues, didſt bring into the world the author of grace &amp; waſt thy ſelfe repleniſhed with all fullnes therof, and art as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall conduct to conuay his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine fauours vnto vs; let vs ſo be ſtrengthned by thy diuine fauour
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18588:47"/>and holy interceſſion, that we may in ſuch ſort ſhew our ſelues true children of diuine grace, that thou maiſt not refuſe to be our Mother, or deny vs to be thy children; but according to thy Name, as thou art called <hi>Mother of mercy,</hi> for the loue thou ſheweſt vnto repentant ſinners; ſo alſo ſhew thy ſelfe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of diuine grace,</hi> in obtayning for vs ſome portion of that cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall gift which may make vs tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heyrs of that eternal Kingdom, of which this diuine grace is the only pledge, and ſureſt warrant. Amen. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="meditation">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:18588:48"/>
               <head>THE VII. MEDITATION. <hi>Mater puriſsima, ora pro nobis.</hi> Moſt pure Mother, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IN this Title of Purity we will not ſpeake of the Virginall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Queene of heauen, of which we haue ſayd ſomewhat al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in the Title of <hi>Virgin of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins,</hi> and ſhall adde more in the Meditations following: but we will now ſpeake of the vnſpotted Purity of the B. Virgin, from the blemiſh and ſtaine of ſinne.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt therefore we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how free this B. Virgin did alwayes keep her ſelfe from the foule and vgly blot of all mortall ſinne. Our firſt Mother <hi>Eue</hi> vvas called the <hi>Mother of the liuing,</hi> but was indeed Mother of the dead;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18588:48"/>for being ſeduced and ſubdued by the ſerpents ſubtilty, ſhe intiſed &amp; deceaued <hi>Adam</hi> to ſinne alſo, by whoſe diſobedience we all remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſubiect not only to death, but alſo vnto thouſands of miſeryes. But the B. Virgin, <hi>mutans Euae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> changing the name of <hi>Eue,</hi> did alwayes remayne vnited with God, and ſo cruſhed and bruized the Serpents head, that withal his crafty guiles and ſubtile trickes he could neuer ſupplant this gracious Queene, to giue but the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent vnto any vnlawfull act, or to ſpeake any hurtfull word, or haue the leaſt thought that might tend into any mortall ſinne: but ſhe alwayes kept her ſelfe moſt pure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n thought, vvord, and deed, and therefore moſt vvorthily deſerues the ſhining Title of moſt <hi>Pure</hi> and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18588:49"/>
                  <hi>Vnſpotted;</hi> giuing vs alſo courage when the foule monſter and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of mankind ſhall aſſault vs, to caſt our eyes vpon her, and ſay, <hi>Mater puriſsima, ora pro nobis,</hi> moſt pure Mother pray for vs. For the Diuell being exceſſiue proud, and inſolent, and hauing beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered and foyled by this glorious Queene, he dares not ſtay at the inuocation of her ſacred Name, nor can he endure to heare vs call for her ſoueraigne ayde and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, vvho is moſt pure, and moſt ready to help all thoſe vvho truely call vpon her.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond poynt yealdeth vs matter to meditate and ponder, how this pure and vnſpotted Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin-Mother, did not only keep her ſelfe free from all tainture of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinne, but did alſo auoyd the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18588:49"/>leaſt blemiſh of any venial ſinne, into which ordinarily euen the moſt Iuſt do fall, and that many tymes a day, as holy Writ doth witnes in theſe words: <hi>Septies in die cadit iuſtus, &amp; reſurgit:</hi> ſeauen tymes a day the iuſt man doth fal, &amp; riſe againe, which is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of ſmal ſinnes, and light offences. Neither are they tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med light, becauſe we do careleſly commit them, or make light of them (for one of them ought not to be committed to ſaue the whole world) but they be ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be of their own nature ſuch, as they do not extinguiſh the grace of God in the Iuſt man, nor are directly againſt Charity, &amp; therefore may ſtand both with grace and charity, and may the eaſier be forgiuen. Yet I ſay from
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18588:50"/>the little blemiſhes that taint euen the beſt, this B. Virgin was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes free, euer ſo perfectly vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Almighty God, and ſo wholy imployed in his diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, that the leaſt blaſt of any ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial ſinne, could neuer ſtayne the flouriſhing beauty of her excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertues. This conſideration made S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſay, <hi>Cùm de peccatis agitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. l. de natur. &amp; grat. cap. <hi>36.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nolo de B. Virgine mentionem fieri,</hi> When there is any ſpeach of ſinne, I will haue no mention made of the B. Virgin; for right well he knew how free ſhe was, not only from the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wounds of mortall ſinne, but alſo from the leaſt ſhaddow of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny veniall ſinne, and therefore moſt pure and worthyly called v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon by that Title, <hi>Most pure Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, pray for vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:18588:50"/> 3. The third point is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the vndefiled purity of the B. Virgin, euen from the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſpot of originall ſinne, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which all the children of <hi>Adam</hi> were ſubiect, if they deſcended by naturall propagation, as this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Queene did; yet by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar priuiledge was ſhe excepted from that generall law. For the infinite wiſedome of Almighty God did not thinke it fit that ſhe who was choſen from all eternity to be the Mother vnto his only Sonne, ſhould euer be ſayd to haue been in the power of Sathan. And therfore with his particular grace did preuent the effect of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral curſe, whereby our moſt pure Mother did remaine moſt beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the ſight of God, pleaſing vnto his Sonne; and euen from
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18588:51"/>her firſt beginning, in her imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Conception, eſpouſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Holy Ghoſt by heauenly grace. And by this indeed the Title of <hi>Moſt pure</hi> doth fitly agree vnto her. For we may ſay ſhe was pure in that ſhe fled all mortal ſin; yet more pure in that no veniall ſinne could euer taint her; but in this moſt pure, that euen from the ſpot of originall ſinne ſhe was preſerued, and by ſingular fauour exempted from that curſe, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed befitted the choſen Mother of God.</p>
               <p>O moſt pure, and vnſpotted Mother,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> caſt thy diuin eyes vpon thy deuout ſeruants, and let not the impurity of our former ſins, defile vs. We muſt all confeſſe, we are conceaued the children o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wrath, and borne in wickedness
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18588:51"/>by originall ſinne; yet, <hi>Mater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsima ora pro nobis,</hi> moſt pure Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, pray for vs: That as we haue by Baptiſme drowned the one, ſo we may, by true Pennance and Contrition waſh away the other, that being ſprinkled with the dew of diuine grace, and made more white then ſnow, we may appear moſt ioyfully in the ſight of thy ſweet Son, whoſe pretious bloud hath beene the medicinable riuer <hi>Iordan,</hi> to waſh away our Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy. Pray for vs, O ſacred Queen, that we may ſo imitate this thy Angelicall purity, &amp; be moſt pure children of a moſt vnſpotted Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Amen. <hi>O glorioſa Domina &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="meditation">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:18588:52"/>
               <head>THE VIII. MEDITATION. <hi>Mater Caſtiſsimae, ora pro nobis.</hi> Moſt chaſt Mother, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>VVE haue already in the fourth Meditation ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the excellency of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity of this powerfull Queene. Now are we to conſider the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned title of her ſingular Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, by which we ſalute her whé we ſay, <hi>Most chaſt Mother, pray for vs</hi> In this Angelical vertue of Chaſtity, I find three degrees, which if we conſider how emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent they were all in the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, we ſhall eaſily perceaue how worthily ſhe is called <hi>Mater Caſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt degree of Chaſtity is coniugall, that is, ſuch as may
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18588:52"/>be kept betwixt man and wife, at leaſt for a tyme, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelleth thoſe that be maryed to do, that they might pray the better, and be the fitter for the ſeruice of God. This degree of Chaſtity, the B. Virgin had in the higheſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; for although ſhe were truly deſpouſed to S. <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and was his vndoubted wife; yet as S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſayth, he was but <hi>Cuſtos integerrimae Caſtitatis,</hi> the keeper of her moſt pure Chaſtity. For as the ſacred Text of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth lay open vnto vs, before they euer came togeather the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the incarnation of Chriſt was knowne, though not as a Myſtery; and therfore, as S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> writeth, <hi>Celabat ſilentio, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us Mysterium neſciebat,</hi> he coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed with ſilence the myſtery he
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18588:53"/>knew not: So that the B. Virgin was a wife, but alwayes moſt chaſt, and therefore called a <hi>Most chaſt Mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond degree of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity is of holy Widdowes, who after the death of their husbands moſt earneſtly imbrace this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly vertue. In this alſo the B. Virgin was moſt eminent: for it is very probable that <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi> was departed this life before the Paſſion of our Sauiour. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt commended his B. Mother to S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> as himſelfe witneſſeth; after whoſe death, the B. Virgin lead a widdowes life, and was the mirrour of all chaſt Widdowes. Beſides ſhe may be ſayd to be a Widdow after the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, in that, ſhe was left as it were, <hi>Viduata colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:18588:53"/>a doue without her mate, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes groaning, euer mourning like the forſaken Turtle, vntill ſhe came to meet him againe in the happy pallace of eternal bliſſe: ſhe therefore was a moſt chaſt Widdovv, and that in a moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable manner.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third and moſt renovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned degree of this noble Vertue, is called Virginal Chaſtity, which is, vvhen Virgins wholy dedicate themſelues vnto Chriſt by holy vow, and take him for their only ſpouſe, as the B. Virgin vvas the firſt that euer did, binding her ſelfe by vow of perpetuall chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be vvholy and only his; after whoſe rare example ſo many thouſandes of holy Virgins haue follovved vvith vndaunted cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and many of them loſt their
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18588:54"/>liues in the iuſt defence of this worthyly eſteemed vertue. And how eminent the B. Virgin was in this, we may eaſily gather out of that which hath beene ſayd of her <hi>Chast Virginity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by theſe three degrees, which we find moſt eminent in the B. Virgin, we may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue with how great reaſon ſhe is intitled, <hi>Mater caſtiſsima,</hi> moſt chaſt Mother. We muſt therefore mooue our ſelues with an earneſt deſire, &amp; louing affection toward this vertue, and no leſſe to wardes the B. Virgin, who ſo greatly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled in it.<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> And with theſe deſires we muſt fall downe before this <hi>chaſt Mother</hi> to implore her ayde and help, for the better accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing what we deſire, and ſay <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſingularis, inter omnes mitis, nos
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18588:54"/>culpis ſolutos, mites fac &amp; caſtos:</hi> Virgin without peere, &amp; amongſt all others moſt mild, we being cleanſed from our ſinnes by thy holy interceſſion, make vs alſo both mild &amp; chaſt. Amen. Then we may conclude, to this effect, with the deuout Hymne, <hi>Aue Maris ſtella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="meditation">
               <head>THE IX. MEDITATION. <hi>Mater Inuiolata, ora pro nobis.</hi> Vndefiled Mother, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>BY this moſt worthy Title is ſignifyed vnto vs the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble combination of the dignity of Virginity, ioyned with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Mother;</hi> a thing naturally impoſſible, and only by the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent hand of God to be broght
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18588:55"/>to paſſe. Therefore in this Title we are to conſider this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full worke of admiration, and to prayſe the diuine prouidence of Almighty God; who to prepare our hard hart to the great myſtery of the Incarnation of his only Sonne, would beginne with this admirable Conception, long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diſcouered by the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſay, Ecce Virgo concipiet, &amp; pariet filium:</hi> Behold a Virgin ſhal conceaue, and bring forth a Son, that is, neither the ſtrang con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, nor deſyred birth of that miraculous Sonne, ſhould any way impeach or diminiſh the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Virginity, &amp; yet he ſhould bring with him the fecundity of a Mother: therfore the ſayd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet as it were inuiting vs to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, ſayth, <hi>Ecce,</hi> behold.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18588:55"/>And the holy Prophet <hi>Hieremy</hi> called it <hi>Nouum,</hi> a new thing, as indeed it was both ſtrang &amp; new. She was a chaſt Virgin, yet a fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itfull Mother, and therfore a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin-Mother, <hi>Mater inuiolata,</hi> an vndefiled Mother. For how could ſhe be defiled, who conceaued by the worke of the Holy Ghoſt? how could ſhe be ſpotted, who as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> teacheth, <hi>Corpus ſine corporis contagione concepit,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued the ſacred body of Chriſt without any contagion of her owne.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore by this both prayſe the goodnes of God, for choſing the B. Virgin an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this diuin miracle of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles;<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> and alſo congratulate our happieſt Queene, that ſhe was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to ſo high a dignity, &amp; of ſo
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18588:56"/>great eſteeme in the ſight of God, and ſo the more powerfull to help vs, when we ſay, <hi>Mater inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ora pro nobis,</hi> vndefiled mother, pray for vs. For calling vpon her by this diuine Title, is as much as to ſay, for the loue of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine worke of admiration, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou wert made Mother of God remayning a Virgin, pray for vs, For the ioy thou didſt conceaue in this diuine Myſtery, pray for vs. In honour of this vnſpeakable combinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the venerable title of Mother, with the ſhinning Iuſtre of virginity, pray for vs: &amp; obtayne, that by thy powerfull prayers and holy interceſſion we may be worthy to conceaue thy Bleſſed Sonne ſweet Ieſus in our ſoules. Amen. <hi>Salue Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="meditation">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:18588:56"/>
               <head>THE X. MEDITATION. <hi>Mater Intemgrata, ora pro nobis.</hi> Vntouched Mother, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>BY this <hi>Epitheton,</hi> we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider another excellent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the B. Virgins chaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne. For as in the former title we did contemplate how ſhe was Mother, yet without all ſtayne of her angelicall purity: ſo heere we may ponder the vnſpotted beauty of her chaſt virginity, not any whit diminiſhed, or ſo much as touched vvith that wonderfull acceſſe of this new title of <hi>Mother,</hi> and therfore moſt aptly ſhe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled, <hi>An vntouched Mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lilly which is the chief ſymbole and figure of Chaſtity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of it owne nature of moſt dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18588:57"/>condition. To the eye moſt pleaſing, to the ſmel moſt fragra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; but if it come to be handled, or touched, it is ſo ſoon bleamiſhed, that it looſeth both the exquiſite ſmell, and the excellent beauty, ſo the renowned vertue of chaſt Virgins will not admit the leaſt touch of any earthly affection, &amp; worldly loue, without a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſtayne and vtter diſgrace of ſo rare a vertue. And becauſe this beautifull <hi>Lilly of the valleys,</hi> the B. Mother of God, was <hi>Lilium in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpinas,</hi> a Lilly a midſt thornes; yet euer vnſpotted, vndefiled, &amp; vntouched, therefore ſhe is called <hi>Mater intemerata.</hi> Of this moſt pure Virgin the holy Catholike Church ſingeth: <hi>Benedicta &amp; vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilis es Virgo Maria, quae ſine tactu pudoris inuentaes Mater Saluatoris.</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:18588:57"/>Bleſſed &amp; venerable art thou, O Virgin Mary, who without any touch of thy chaſtity didſt becom the Mother of God.</p>
               <p>Let vs ſee further how this admirable worke was effected. She, as the moſt beautifull flower of virginity, was repleniſhed with great aboundance of grace, and ſo ſaluted by the heauenly Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, when he denounced vnto her that ſhe ſhould become Mother of God: yet our ſacred Queene replyed, in the behalfe of her vnſpotted purity, asking how that could come to paſſe, being ſhe was a vowed Virgin? To which the Angell anſwered, that it was a worke to be accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the diuine help of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt; and therefore the child ſhe was to beare, was to be the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18588:58"/>Sonne of God. The humble obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Virgin, diuing in the depth of her owne nothing, anſwered withall ſubmiſſion, and moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reſignation, <hi>Ecce Ancilla Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, fiat mihi ſecundum verbum tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> Behold the hand-mayd of our Lord, let his wil be fulfilled in me, according to thy ſpeach. And ſo by this humble conſent, by this admirable <hi>fiat,</hi> ſhe became indeed Mother of God. Behold then how ſhe was made Mother, yet with the integrity of her virginall cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity. By a word, with a <hi>fiat,</hi> the heauens were created, the Sunne, the Moone, and all the glittering light of heauen; by a word, with a <hi>fiat</hi> the earth was made, the Sea, the Land, and all thinges els that ſea and land contaynes: now (O miracle of miracles) by one word
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18588:58"/>by one <hi>fiat</hi> of a Virgin, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is made Man, conceaued by a chaſt conſent, borne of a pure and vnſpotted Mother, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter intemerata.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O diuine Mother, let the ſweet perfumes of this Angelicall vertue, ſo enter into our ſenſes, ſo wrappe our vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> and ſo rauiſh our will, that we may admit no other thought, or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, no other affections or deſires, but ſuch as may bring forth this ſweet ſmell, this fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant perfume of purity; that we may be grateful in the eyes of our Creator, pleaſing in the preſence of our Redeemer, and in thy ſight worthy to be beloued. Amen. <hi>Aue Maris stella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="meditation">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:18588:59"/>
               <head>THE XI. MEDITATION. <hi>Mater amabilis, ora pro nobis.</hi> Louely Mother, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>MANY cauſes may be aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; many reaſons found why the B. Virgin is ſayd to be <hi>louely,</hi> which I will endeauour to reduce to three general heads, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will not exceed my won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted breuity.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt cauſe or reaſon, which both maketh her louely, &amp; moueth vs to loue her, may be her excellent beauty, which did ſo abound in this <hi>louely</hi> Queen, as the like hath not beene found in any other. For as our Sauiour was the moſt beautifull of men according to the kingly propheſy, <hi>Specioſus forma prae filijs hominum,</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:18588:59"/>beautifull and comely in ſhape be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſonnes of men: ſo the B. Virgin was moſt beautifull of all the daughters of women; that whoſoeuer ſhould behould them both, might ſay, ſhe could not be Mother, but of ſo fayre a Sonne, nor he Sonne, but of ſo beautifull a Mother. And this beauty of the B. Virgin (of externall beauty &amp; comlines we ſpeake) did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in a moſt perfect proportion of all the lineaments of her ſacred body, whereby ſhe was <hi>pulcherima mulierum,</hi> the moſt beautifull of women, and therfore moſt <hi>louely</hi> in that reſpect. Neither was her virginal comelynes ſuch as vſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth ſtir vp wanton luſtes, or inflame bad deſires; but altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo far contrary, that who ſo ſhould behold the beautifull bluſh
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18588:60"/>of her modeſt and virginall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, could not choſe, but be inflamed with moſt chaſt deſires and Feruent loue towardes this vertuous Queene.</p>
               <p>This then may be giuen for the firſt reaſon of this louely title, <hi>Mater amabilis.</hi> And in this beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I include her grauity in ſpeach, her modeſty in countenance, her grace in conuerſation, &amp; the due proportion of all her actions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alwayes guided and gouerned by her inward vertues, of vvhich heere after we ſhall haue occaſion to ſpeake more. <hi>Iudith</hi> being to worke the ouerthrow of proud <hi>Holofernes,</hi> in defence of her citty and people, adorned and decked her ſelfe withall the richeſt iewels and beſt or naments ſhe had, and made herſelfe as beautiful as with
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:18588:60"/>her beſt skil ſhe could, ouer which Almighty God caſt a ſplendour, of which holy Writ telleth vs: <hi>Cui Dominus quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> contulit ſplendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iud. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> vnto which beauty our Lord alſo added a luſtre. And ſhall we not then thinke of the B. Virgin, vvhoſe figure <hi>Iudith</hi> did beare, that after nature had ſhewed her ſelfe in this admirable worke, that our Lord alſo added the chiefeſt grace of her excellent beauty? How then could ſhe be but <hi>louely,</hi> and therfore, <hi>Mater amabilis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond cauſe, and more chiefe reaſon of her comelynes (which ſhall be the ſecond point) is her invvard beauty, that is, her excellent vertue, by the vvhich deſeruedly ſhe may be ſayd tvvice beautifull, and ſo in the Canticles ſhe is, and that vvith a kind of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18588:61"/>
                  <hi>Quàm pulchra es amica mea, quàm pulchra es!</hi> Hovv beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull thou art my beloued, hovv beautifull! Beautifull by reaſon of her outward comelynes, but much more by reaſon of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard vertues: For <hi>Omnis gloria filiae Regis ab intus,</hi> all the glory of the Kings daughter is from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>Heere therfore we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſingular grace &amp; comely meeting of all vertues in this gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Queene; her profound hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; her humble obedience; her ſhining purity; her vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble modeſty; her burning charity; and moſt perfect reſignation of her ſelfe into the handes of God, withall the reſt of her excellent vertues in due tyme and place, in the beſt manner, guided by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18588:61"/>with exact obſeruation of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery circumſtance, and as it were <hi>Caſtrorum acies ordinata,</hi> an army of ſouldiers well ordered. This conſidered as an harmony of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect muſicke, where no voyce miſſeth his right note and tune, no inſtrument iarreth, no ſound out of order, muſt make vs of force to ſtand amazed at the rare compoſition of her inward beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the ſingular concord of her matchles vertues, &amp; thus be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to loue &amp; affect her moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy perſon, wherin we find them ſo perfectly vnited, and by which indeed ſhe is <hi>Mater amabilis,</hi> a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely Mother.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The laſt generall reaſon, and the third point, is to meditat how much we are beloued of her, and in how princely and bountifull
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18588:62"/>manner ſhe dealeth with vs. For nothing moueth more to loue, then to know we are beloued, &amp; ſince loue can neuer be repayed but by loue, ſeeing ſhe hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelfe ſo louely a Mother vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, we are bound in all grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and dutifull reſpect, to the vttermoſt of our power, to requite it. She had but one only Sonne, whome ſhe loued far more then al the Mothers in the world loue their children; yet was ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that in his infancy he ſhould be our companion, at his laſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per our food, at his death the price of our Redemption, and now ſhe continually prayeth for vs, that he may be our endles ioy, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines. How could ſhe ſhevv her ſelfe more louing, or hovv more louely, then like another <hi>Abraham</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:18588:62"/>to offer vp her owne beloued Son at the commandment of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, only for our good? Let vs therefore louingly and deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay <hi>Mater amabilis ora pro nobis,</hi> louely Mother, pray for vs. <hi>O glorioſa Domina &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XII. MEDITATION. <hi>Mater Admirabilis, ora pro nobis.</hi> Admirable Mother, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IN this admirable title we muſt firſt ſuppoſe the force of this world <hi>Admirable;</hi> for it doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port ſome ſtrange and wounder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing which is cauſe of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: and from hence miracles do take their name, becauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beyond our naturall reach, they make vs admire. But if we
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18588:63"/>conſider the vertuous life, the miraculous death or departure, &amp; the exceſſiue glory of the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, we ſhall not only ſee hovv iuſtly this Title is applyed vnto her, but alſo vvith how great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we may ſay, <hi>Mater admirabilis,</hi> admirable Mother pray for vs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt then, in a briefe and compendious manner, we are to call to mind the admirable life of the B. Virgin. Admirable was her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ception, obtayned by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and vow, denounced by an Angel, of aged &amp; barren parents, without the ſpot of originall ſin: all theſe thinges are great cauſes of admiration. Admirable was her ſtrang Natiuity, borne in the field (as S. <hi>Iohn Damaſcen</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth) in a certaine grange of her Fathers, among the ſweet tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18588:63"/>notes of innocent bleating Lambes, as one who vvas to be the Mother to the immaculate Lambe of God, deſigned to be ſlaine for ranſome of vs all; or as one who vvas to bring vs the true ſheep-heard of our ſoules, vvho would haue moſt tender care of vs. Admirable, in that ſhe vvas preuented vvith the vſe of reaſon either in her Mothers wombe, or at the third yeare of her age, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe vvas offered vp and preſented in the Temple. Admirable in her life and conuerſation, and aboue al admirable in that ſhe vvas both Mother and Virgin. Admirable alſo in her conſtancy, at the foot of the croſſe, admirable in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, in grace, and in all kind of vertue. Theſe thinges, and the like conſidered, will giue vs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18588:64"/>vnderſtanding how ſhe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Mater admirabilis,</hi> an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Mother.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond point is to pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the admirable departure of her Bleſſed ſoule out of her ſacred body, and out of this life. For ſhe liued 72. yeares, dyed not of any diſeaſe, or diſtemper of diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red humors, but of pure loue and longing deſire to be with Chriſt her deareſt Sonne, which was an admirable death. Beſides, all the Apoſtles then liuing were mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly gathered togeather at her departure, and moſt ſolemly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the dutyes of her exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies. After three dayes, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour deſcended from heauen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed with his Quires of Angells, and aſſumpted her into heauen body and ſoule, where ſhe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18588:64"/>vvas ſeated in ſuch maieſty, and crowned with ſo great glory, there to raigne for euer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third point, ſhall be to admire this Elected Queene of Angells paſſing through the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed company of Virgins, leauing behind her the conſtant Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, glorious Martyrs the holy Apoſtles, Patriarkes, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; mounting aboue the nine Quires of Angells, ſeated aboue the Cherubims and Seraphims in a Royall Throne by her ſelfe, as beſt befitted ſo glorious &amp; admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Mother. And if we will at length come to the height of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, let vs behould this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Empreſſe veſted with the Sunne, crowned with ſtars, and treading the Moone vnder her vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious feet, that is, in exceeding
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18588:65"/>great glory, anſwerable both to her admirable titles, and ſingular vertues. For as we haue already meditated, ſhe was enriched with more grace and ſpirituall gifts, then al Saints and Angels beſides, and therfore muſt haue a Crown of glory anſwerable thereunto; which muſt exceed the glorious crowns of them all. And by theſe three points we ſee how ſhe was admirable in life, admirable in her departure, admirable in glory, &amp; ſo moſt worthily called <hi>Mater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirabilis,</hi> an admirable Mother.</p>
               <p>O moſt admirable, and euer happy Mother, who art in all points ſo much to be admyred;<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> be now vnto vs a powerful aduocate that we may (as far as our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes will permit) imitate thy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable vertues in our life; that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:18588:65"/>we may find comfort at our death and deſerue to receaue a Crown of glory with thee in heauen for all eternity. Amen. <hi>O glorioſa Domina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XIII. MEDITATION. <hi>Mater Creatoris, ora pro nobis.</hi> Mother of the Creatour, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>MANY of theſe Titles are the ſame in effect, with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God;</hi> yet we will ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, that we may conceaue ſome particuler reaſon of this, &amp; the like titles, whereby the great dignity of the B. Mother of God may the more appeare. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſometymes we vſe to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute Omnipotency to God the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18588:66"/>Father, Wiſedome to the Sonne, and Bounty to the holy Ghoſt; yet being all but one God, they are all equally Omnipotent, Wiſe, and Bountifull: And becauſe in their outward actions (as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines ſpeake <hi>ad extra</hi>) they work inſeparably, ſo that whatſoeuer the one doth, they are ſayd to worke all three togeather; Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is as well attributed to the Sonne, as the Father, and in this ſenſe the B. Virgin is called <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Creatoris,</hi> Mother of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour. For indeed ſo he was, ſince as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſayth, <hi>omnia per ipſum facta ſunt,</hi> all thinges were made by him. Heere therfore we are to conſider how the infinite wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God found out ſo ſweet meanes to communicate himſelfe to man, as to ſhut himſelfe within
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18588:66"/>the B. Virgins ſacred wombe, whereby we worthily ſay, <hi>Quem caeli capere non poterant, tuo gremio contulisti:</hi> He whome the wide heauens could not contayne, thou haſt incloſed in thy ſacred womb.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly conſider, that the B. Virgin being mother of our, &amp; her Creatour, ſhe is the fitteſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troneſſe for all ſinners to choſe, that the worke of their creation may not be fruſtrate; ſeeing then that God hath created all thinges for vs, and our ſelues for himſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t vs make recourſe to the Bleſſed Mother of the Creatour of all things, that by her powerfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, we may vſe them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the end for which they were created, &amp; make of them a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adder to clime and aſcend to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eight of that dignity, for which
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18588:67"/>we vvere ordayned by the eternal Prouidence of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly we may contemplat how Creation is nothing els, but the making of a thing of nothing; and this can only be performed by the Omnipotent hand of God: we then conſidering our ſelues to be nothing, we may ſay with the Kingly Prophet, <hi>Cor mundum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rea in me Deus, &amp; ſpiritum rectum innoua in viſceribus meis:</hi> Create a cleane hart in me, O God, and renew a right ſpirit in my bowels ſince of this nothing of ours, he is able to make moſt excellent work by the ſending his diuine ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. For as we ſee the ſcorched fields in the middſt of Summer refreſhed by ſome gentle ſhower; or the face of the earth after a long and tedious winter,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:18588:67"/>renewed by a pleaſant ſpring: ſo doth the preſence of this diuine ſpirit make vs all new againe. Therefore if we feele our vertues dying, or our reſolution fayling, let vs not ceaſe to cry, <hi>Emitte ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum tuum &amp; creabuntur, &amp; reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uabis faciem terrae:</hi> Send forth, O Lord, thy holy ſpirit, &amp; al things now turned to nothing wil recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue another being, and thou wilt renew the face of the earth: and to obtayne our petition of the Creatour of all thinges, let vs not be vnmindfull of his Bleſſed Mother, but with this worthy title ſay, <hi>Mater Creatoris ora pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>obis,</hi> Mother of our Creatour pray for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="meditation">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:18588:68"/>
               <head>THE XIV. MEDITATION. <hi>Mater Saluatoris, ora pro nobis.</hi> Mother of our Sauiour, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>THIS moſt Venerable Title doth inuite vs to contemplat a while vpon the ſweet name of Ieſus; for Ieſus and Sauiour are the ſame; and to be Mother of our Sauiour is to be the Mother of Ieſus: let vs therfore vvith atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diligently ponder the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the gift, that our deuotion towardes the giuer may increaſe the more.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt then let vs conſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how vve vvere all loſt, in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall boundage, in euerlaſting thraldome and captiuity of ſinne vntill this B. Mother brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:18588:68"/>forth a Sauiour, a Redeemer, vvhoſe moſt pretious bloud vvas the only ranſome of our ſinnes, vvhoſe death vvas vnto vs life, and vvhoſe bleeding woundes vvere the only cure and moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne balme of our feſtred ſoules. For darke night ſhe brought vs cheerefull day; for a hard and ſharp winter, a ſvveet &amp; pleaſant ſpring; for our mortall vvounds, immortall medicines; for our pining ſoules, bread of life; and laſtly for all our miſery, the Father of mercyes. This the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Angell ſong vnto the ſeely ſheep hards, in the happy night of his Natiuity, <hi>Natus eſt vobis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Saluator, qui est Chriſtus Ieſus:</hi> You haue this day born vnto you (of the B. Virgin) a Sauiour, which is Chriſt Ieſus. Our loſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:18588:69"/>taſt by this ſvveet Name muſt be reſtored, for he is hony in the mouth: our eares accuſtomed to iarring diſcordes, muſt be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by this ſvveet muſicke, for he is melody in the eare: our harts oppreſſed vvith grief &amp; ſorrovv, muſt be repleniſhed vvith ioy, for he is gladnes in the hart.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly to diue yet deeper into the greatnes of this benefit, conſider vvhat ioy a poore priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner vvould find in his hart, if co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to a moſt ignominious &amp; cruell death, one ſhould come &amp; louingly offer him his pardon? What comfort ſhould one find if being by ſentence iudged to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall baniſhment, a fauourable ſentence ſhould recall him, and place him again in his former ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ancient dignity? Then
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:18588:69"/>let vs apply this to the B. Virgin, vvho brought vs forth a Sauiour after the ſharp ſentence of death, to pronounce vs a fauourable par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; and after the doome of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual baniſhment, from the ſight of God, for hauing incurred his high diſpleaſure, he hath brought vs backe againe, &amp; made vs Sons of his heauenly Father, &amp; fellow-heires in this ovvne kingdome.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly vve are to conſider the great part our B. Lady had in this happy vvork of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being choſen by Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Wiſedome to be his Mother, and the flovving conduit of all happynes to vs, that vve might vvith great deuotion ſay, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Saluatoris ora pro nobis,</hi> Mother of our Sauiour, pray for vs. And vvhat better petition can
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18588:70"/>we make vnto her, but that vve may be grateful for ſo great a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, that now the price of our Redemption being payd, we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect not to make our beſt profit and commodity thereof, that he may be truly and indeed a Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our vnto vs, as ſhe truely was a Mother vnto him. For how great might our ingratitude be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if after ſo long ſeeking vs, &amp; ſo deare buying vs, we ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect his bountifull mercyes, and ſeeme to be careles of his vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued liberalityes.</p>
               <p>O moſt Bleſſed &amp; euer hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Mother of Ieſus, aſſiſt with thy holy prayers,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> we beſeech thee, thy deuout ſuppliants, that thy ſweet Sonne Ieſus may be vnto vs Ieſus, that is a Sauiour. Behold vve cal vpon thee, Mother of our Sauiour
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18588:70"/>to be ſaued, Mother of Ieſus to be healed, Mother of God to be made his true and faythfull children by thy powerfull interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, throgh the infinite merits of the Bleſſed fruit of thy holy wombe. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XV. MEDITATION. <hi>Virgo Prudentiſsima, ora pro nobis.</hi> Moſt prudent Virgin, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>THAT we may the better vnderſtand the reaſon why the B. Queene of Angells is called <hi>Most prudent,</hi> we will produce three or foure examples of prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Matrones in the old Teſtament, who may ſeeme to haue borne the type and figure of this prudent Virgin.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:18588:71"/> 1. The firſt we read in the booke of <hi>Iudith,</hi> where this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous &amp; prudent matron, ſeeing the extreme affliction of her belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nation to increaſe in ſuch ſort that the wiſeſt of them were thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it beſt to yeald themſelues vnto the merciles handes of their proude enemyes; ſhe prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the direction of Almighty God behaued her ſelfe with ſuch prudence and fortitude, that ſhe both foyled her enemies, and got her people a moſt famous and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant victory: for which ſhe was by the high Prieſt, and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of the people denounced bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and all the vulgar ſort anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Amen. This no doubt was an act not only of inuincible for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, but alſo of admirable pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. But if we turne our eyes
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:18588:71"/>vnto the ſacred Virgin, we ſhall find that ſhe hath deliuered vs from a ſtronger enemy, preſerued vs from greater danger then tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall death, foyled &amp; ouercome a prouder foe then <hi>Holofernes;</hi> and therefore with great reaſon we may ſay, <hi>Tu gloria Hieruſalem, tu laetitiae Iſraël, tu honorificentia popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li noſtri:</hi> Thou art the glory of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> thou the ioy of <hi>Iſraël,</hi> thou the honour and renowne of our Nation. She bedecked with the priceleſſe ornament of vertue, her ſoule adorned with the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and beames of diuine grace, and aſſiſted by the potent hand of Almighty God, came to tread our ancient enemy Sathan vnder her conquering feet.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond act of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Prudence, we read in the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:18588:72"/>booke of <hi>Heſter,</hi> how for the good of her Nation,<note place="margin">Heſt. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> ſhe aduentured to enter before the King, was inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his golden Rod, wher with her great prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhe ſo wrought the King, that ſhe obtayned not only the liues of her deare Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, but alſo great and ample priuileges for them; yea &amp; ſeuere chaſtizement of thoſe that ſought her, and her Countryes deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. No leſſe the B. Virgin, after Sathan had conſpired the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of mankind, entring be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King of heauen, with her profound humility, ſo prudently ſhe behaued her ſelfe, that ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Mother vnto his only Son, who both deliuered vs from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall perill, and made vs of the happy number of the children of God, and heyres to the kingdom
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:18588:72"/>of heauen, which by our diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence we had loſt, and therefore moſt worthily ſhe is called <hi>Virgo Prudentiſsima,</hi> a moſt prudent Vigin.</p>
               <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Iud. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> The third and fourth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample we haue in <hi>Iahel</hi> &amp; <hi>Abigaël</hi> the one vanquiſhing proud <hi>Siſirae</hi> the fierce enemy of the Iewes;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 25.</note> the other appeafing the fell wrath of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> againſt her fooliſh husband, vvhen he was in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life. But hovv often hath this moſt prudent Virgin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuered vs from our cruell perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utors, who like roaring Lyons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeke day and night whome they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay deuoure, &amp; how many times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath ſhe appeaſed the iuſt wrath of God, kindled againſt vs for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur foule offences, &amp; brought vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gaine into his gracious fauour.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:18588:73"/>
               <p> O moſt prudent Virgin, by this we ſee,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> how fittly this Title doth agree vnto thee; wherefore as by thee we are deliuered from ſo manifold dangers, &amp; by whoſe holy interceſſion we receaue ſo many &amp; gracious fauours, let thy moſt prudent counſell ſo direct vs, that we may auoyd all danger of ſinne, &amp; keep our ſelues in the fauour of thy B. Sonne Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XVI. MEDITATION. <hi>Virgo Veneranda, ora pro nobis.</hi> Venerable Virgin, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>THIS worthy Title, doth manifeſt vnto vs the honour due vnto the B. Virgin, which beeing threefold, doth yield vs three ſubſtantiall groundes for
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:18588:73"/>this preſent Meditation.</p>
               <p>The firſt kind of honour is called <hi>Ciuill,</hi> which is due vnto great Perſonages, by reaſon of their Nobility, Place, Eſtate, or the like. The ſecond is <hi>Religious</hi> worſhip or honour, which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to vertuous and holy men, as they are indued with excellent vertues, eminent graces, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall gifts. The third is <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine</hi> and <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> worſhip ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayning to God, and his Saints in heauen as we ſhal after declare.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt therefore to conſider the B. Virgin according to her lineall deſcent, we ſhall find her worthy to be honoured withall Ciuill honour and dutifull reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect. For if we ſhould demaund vvith holy S. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. ſer. c. <hi>12.</hi> in Apoc.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid ergo ſidereum micat in generatione Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae?</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:18588:74"/>What ſtar-like ſplendor doth ſhine in the generation of the B. Virgin Mary? We may take his owne anſwere in the ſame place, that ſhe ſprung from Kinges, of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of the ſtocke of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that ſhe was foreſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by Figures, foretold by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and by myſticall Oracles inſinuated vnto vs; therefore if we reſpect her Nobility, vve ſhall find that ſhe is worthy of ciuill honour, in the higheſt degree, and ſo in this reſpect <hi>Virgo vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa,</hi> a Virgin worthy to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly if we weigh the great aboundance of her ſingular graces, the greatnes of her excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertues, the number of her ſupernaturall gifts, and laſtly the dignity of Mother of God, we
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:18588:74"/>ſhal find her as worthy of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous honour aboue all others, as ſhe doth exceed them all in her ſingular vertues and vnſpeakable gifts. For as the diuine Wiſedome pronounceth of the prudent wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,<note place="margin">Parab. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Multae filiae congregauerunt diuitias, in ſupergreſſae es vniuerſas,</hi> Many daughters haue gathered riches togeather, but thou haſt gone beyond them all; for we may iuſtly ſay of this ſacred Queene, That many Holy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons in the old law, many ſacred Virgins in the new haue been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with rare vertues, ſingular graces, and merua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lous fauours; but when this glittering ſtar ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, ſhe did as far exceed them all, as the leaſt ſtar is in light infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the Sunne, and therefore moſt worthy of Religious honour
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:18588:75"/>and reſpect, <hi>Virgo veneranda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly if we come to the diuine and ſupernaturall worſhip belonging to God, and his Saints in heauen, we ſhall find her to be preferred before all Saints, &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and inſtalled next vnto God; for as the diuine worſhip of <hi>Latriae</hi> (ſo the Deuines terme it) is due, and giuen to none but to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: ſo vnto his Saints is due the worſhip of <hi>Dulia,</hi> which belongs vnto them, as friends &amp; ſeruants of God, the moſt eminent degree whereof is called <hi>Hyperdulia,</hi> which moſt iuſtly is giuen to the B. Virgin. Loe how vvorthily we do giue vnto her honour and reuerence in all the ſenſes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named: and why ſhould we not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidently fly vnto her in our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſityes and troubles, ſaying <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:18588:75"/>Veneranda ora pro nobis,</hi> Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Virgin pray for vs.</p>
               <p>Heere we ought to ſtir vp our affection towards this happy Queene, and earneſtly to deſyre, that this honour ſo iuſtly due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> may be giuen her by al true Chriſtians, and endeauour to the vttermoſt of our forces to aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce it moſt carefully, procuring that by our negligence it be not hindred: to which effect we muſt deuoutly implore her Motherly help, and powerfull hand. Then may we conclude with this diuin Hymne, <hi>Aue Maris stella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="meditation">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:18588:76"/>
               <head>THE XVII. MEDITATION. <hi>Virgo Praedicandae, era pro nohis.</hi> Virgin worthy of prayſe, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IN this laudable Title, the B Virgin is denounced to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of prayſe and commendation, worthy to be called <hi>Bleſſed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Generations:</hi> but becauſe Prayſe may be giuen vnto this B. Creature three manner of wayes therfore we will a while contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate this threefold branch or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple head of her deſerued prayſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt manner of ſetting forth the B. Virgins prayſe, is in hart, when with a true and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall affection we deſire that ſhe may be honoured and prayſed of all people; &amp; that we do inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:18588:76"/>reioyce from the bottom of our harts of her eternall glory and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting happynes, prayſing the diuine prouidence of Almighty God that hath choſen and elected her to ſo great felicity; and in this deuout cogitation we may wiſh and deſire for her greater honour the vnderſtanding of Cherubims &amp; the burning loue of Seraphims, the better to blaze her worthy prayſe throughout the whole world, and to in flame the harts of all people to loue and affect her: and in this firſt manner of prayſe the firſt ground and foundation of true deuotion doth conſiſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of prayſe is by word, where firſt we may conſider how little we are able to perform in reſpect of what is due vnto her. For how many learned
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:18588:77"/>Fathers, holy men, &amp; great Saints haue ſeriouſly imployed their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py tongues in ſetting forth to the view of the vvorld her rare excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencyes, and yet they haue beene forced to ſay, that they could ſay nothing at all in compariſon of what her heroicall actions haue deſerued. What then ſhal we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume (moſt holy Virgin) to ſpeak of thy prayſe, where ſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout ſeruants of thyne haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged themſelues vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy? Yet B. Queene we know thou doſt not ponder the words, but the will, not the gift, but the loue, as thy B. Sonne did with the poore, yet truly affected vviddow who with ſo great deuotion offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her little mite among the reſt, and therefore by him iudged to haue giuen more then all the reſt.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:18588:77"/>Therefore no gift ſo ſmal, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offered with true deuotion, will be gratefull vnto thee, o B. Virgin. And ſince we neither haue thoſe words which may be ſitting vnto thy greatnes, nor the ſincere deuotion which may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them; yet let theſe weake de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of ours by thy holy interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo increaſe, that it may bring forth fome fruit worthy to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto thee, and gratefull in thy ſight.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third manner of prayſe is <hi>by Worke,</hi> that is, when our workes be ſuch, as they redound to the honour of our B. Lady. For as it vvere not inough for the Iewes to ſay they vvere the Sons of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but they muſt alſo ſhevv the workes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to be the trueſt ſigne and beſt token
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:18588:78"/>of their progeny: ſo it will little auayle vs to ſay we are the deuout children of the B. Virgin, if our life and conuerſation be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to the rule &amp; ſquare of her directions, which are the right patterne &amp; true forme of perfect life; and which vvhen vve fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, vve greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend in her. <hi>S Iohn</hi> not content our loue one towardes another ſhould be in wordes only, but that it ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appeare in deeds, vvriteth, <hi>non diligamus lingua, &amp; ſermone. ſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere &amp; veritaete:</hi> let vs not loue in the tongue, &amp; ſpeach (as vve ſay from the teeth outvvard) but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and in truth: for works are the ſureſt teſtimony vvhich ſpeak the beſt language for all men to vnderſtand.</p>
               <p>O thrice happy they,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> vvho
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:18588:78"/>haue their vvits and vvilis, their minds and harts, vvholy imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the B. Virgin prayſes! It is ſayd, there is a tree called <hi>Perſea,</hi> that hath leaues like a tongue, and fruit like a hart, which ſome wiſe men haue applyed to the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full concord betwixt the hart &amp; the tongue, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tongueſpeaks what the hart thinkes. But how far more beautifull a concord wil there be, when not only the hart and tongue, but alſo the outward works ſhall ſound forth the ſweet muſicke of the B. Virgins prayſes. Doubtles it wil be ſuch as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Quires will not diſdayne to beare a part; &amp; theſe be the three wayes by which euery deuout child of the B. Virgin, ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing her prayſe. O Bleſſed Virgin worthy of greater prayſe, then
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:18588:79"/>humane or Angelical tongue ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> giue vnto thee, graunt that by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holy interceſſion we may ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy our thoughts, wordes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> workes in this diuine harmon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of thy prayſe, that they may turn to the glory of God, to thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp; to the profit of our poor and needy ſoules. Amen. <hi>O glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſa Domina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XVIII. MEDITATION. <hi>Virgo Potens, ora pro nobis.</hi> Potent Virgin, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IN this Title we doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the great power which the B Virgin hath both in heauen &amp; earth: in heauen to obtayne vs graces and fauours, in earth to defend vs from perils &amp; dangers.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:18588:79"/> 1. Firſt then let vs conſider her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower in heauen: for the better vnderſtanding whereof, we will conſider the noble and heroicall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct of <hi>Salomon</hi> the Wiſe, who ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in his throne of State, cauſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is mother to be placed on his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight hand, and ſayd vnto her, Aske what thou wilt, I will not ſay thee nay. If King <hi>Salomon</hi> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his dutifull reſpect vnto his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to make her ſo potent, that whatſoeuer ſhe demaunded, ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould be ſure to obtaine; vvhat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay we thinke our B. Sauiour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vould ſay vnto his louing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when ſhe was ſeated by him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> heauen, but aske whatſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou wilt my deereſt Mother, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vvill not deny thee. For hovv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould ſhe be denied who neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>evv how to aske but wel? And
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:18588:80"/>hovv ſhoud he deny, vvho neuer could deny what vvas asked wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Could Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> be ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefull in the ſight of King <hi>Aſſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> that he bad her aske vvhat th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vvould, if it were the halfe of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kingdome, it ſhould not be gaine ſayd and ſhall we not perſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our ſelues, that our B. Lady i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more gratefull in the ſight of the King of heauen, more pleaſing t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her only Sonne, and therefore more potent to demaund without deniall? Could a vvicked<note n="*" place="margin">Herod.</note> King for a vvanton Daunce make th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> like promiſe of halfe his Kingdom and ſhall vve not beleeue that Chriſt vvould be more bountifu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to his deareſt and Bleſſed Mother vvho neuer diſpleaſed him? L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vs then conclude this point vvith this vndeny able truth, that the B
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:18588:80"/>Virgin is ſo potent in the Court of Heauen, that vvhatſoeuer ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emandeth of her Sonne ſhe ſhall obtaine, and therefore let vs ſay, <hi>Virgo potens, ora pro nobis:</hi> Povv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull Virgin, pray for vs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond point may be to contemplate her great povver on earth, vvhich is nothing els but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he execution of her povver in heauen. For as there her Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y care and tender loue tovvardes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, is to obtayne fauours for vs; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o heere it is to effect, that vve be not fruſtrate of them, vvhich is by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efending vs from our proud ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ies, and ſtrong aduerſaryes the vvorld, the fleſh, and the Diuell; for as the grace of God is the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt benefit vve can enioy on earth; ſo that is the marke at vvhich our ſubtile enemy doth
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:18588:81"/>moſt ayme, thereby to bereaue vs of the right and title we haue to the kingdome of Heauen: where the B. Virgin is moſt watchfull vvith her potent prayers to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs, and to put him to flight, if we deuoutly, as we ought, call vpon her, when we find our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in danger. For as a valiant &amp; ſtout Champion vvould be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med euen to heare the Name of that Woman, who ſhold haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered and foyled him in playne field: ſo this monſter of Pride, Sathan, hauing alwayes beene vanquiſhed by her mighty power, dares not abide ſo much,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> as the naming of that ſacred Name of <hi>Mary.</hi> Therefore as we haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſayd before, let vs fly vnto her as to a Citty of Refuge, &amp; Tower of defence, for ſhe is able to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:18588:81"/>vs; and if we be true Children, ſhe will neuer fayle vs. Hereupon we may conclude this meditation,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> deſyring that in our temporall Croſſes and ſpirituall tentations, we may be myndfull of ſo ſure a refuge, ſo ſweet a ſuccour, ſo ſtrong a Caſtle, and ſo powerfull a defence. <hi>Salue Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XIX. MEDITATION <hi>Virgo Clemens, ora pro nobis.</hi> Clement Virgin, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>CLEMENCY is as it were a branch of compaſſionat mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, by which title we do call vpon the B Virgin, that ſhe may take pitty and compaſſion of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, and commiſeration of our
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:18588:82"/>neceſſities, notwithſtanding our vnworthynes, wherby ſhe makes her ſelfe moſt like vnto her ſweet Sonne, who came into the world to forgiue the fault, and pardon the offender: and by how much greater the fault is proued which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted: by ſo much more the greatnes of the Clemency doth appeare in him that pardoneth. If therfore we conſider the iniury done vnto the B. Virgin, when we offend her ſonne; we ſhall ſee her high Clemency both in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning, of her part, the ſo hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous offence; and alſo her Mercy in intreating before the mercy ſeate for the life of him who hath ſo often deſerued death.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt let vs conſider, how much the obſtinat and ſtony har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Iewes did againſt all iuſtice,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:18588:82"/>law, and conſcience; they abuſed her only Sonne, reiected, ſcorned, and put him to an ignominious death: yet when ſhe heard the pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull voyce of Chriſt vpon the Croſſe crying to his Eternall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pardon them, ſhe alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull of all wrong ſaid; <hi>and I thy mother, do alſo forgiue them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Salmero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould the rare Clemency of the tender bowells of the B. Virgin, whome no wrong could moue, no rage ſtir vp, nor any fury driue from her wonted Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, &amp; moſt mild behauiour. And if thus ſhe prayed for the profeſſed enemyes of Chriſt, why ſhould not they who loue him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire only to ſerue him, confidently implore her gratious help, &amp; ſay, <hi>Virgo Clemens ora pro nobis,</hi> Myld Virgin pray for vs.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:18588:83"/> 2. Secondly, let vs ponder the Ingratitude of man, after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much knowledge of Chriſt, that he doth not ceaſe, (as much a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in him lyeth) to crucify him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine by euery mortall ſynne that he committeth as S. <hi>Paul</hi> writeth Neither doth he this abuſe of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> as Chriſt pleaded for the Iewes; but after the firme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of his God head, his Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Death and Reſurrection, yet after he knowes him to be aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſeated in heauen, when<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he ſhall come to be our terrible Iudge: yet forgetfull of al, he ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to offend him, and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his bleſſed Mother doth interpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> herſelfe, as a wall for <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that is, for him who will truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and call for mercy in tyme with a firme purpoſe and ſtro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:18588:83"/>reſolution neuer againe to offend him.</p>
               <p>O incomparable Clemency of this B. Virgin, who deſireth nothing, but to do good euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe vvho are moſt vvorthy of exceeding great puniſhment!<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> vvho vvould be ſo careleſſe of his owne good, vvho ſo negligent of his ſaluation, as not to fly vnto his Sanctuary, as not to runne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto this fountaine, as not to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ace this ſweet remedy. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore blind man cryed to Ieſus or ſight, and vvould not ceaſe though ſome rebuked him for it) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>til he obteyned the effect of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſire: ſo let vs call vpon this cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and meeke Mother, hovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer others repine therat; let vs vvnto this mild Virgin; Let vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ceaſe to ſay, <hi>Virgo Clemens, ora
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:18588:84"/>pro nobis,</hi> Clement Virgin pray for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XX. MEDITATION <hi>Virgo fidelis, ora pro nobis.</hi> Faithfull Vigin, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>FAITHFVLLNES may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> taken diuers vvayes, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diuers vvayes doth yield <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> copious matter of the B. Virgin prayſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt therfore vve m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> conſider <hi>fidelity</hi> as it doth imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> an excellent act of ſupernature beleefe, in vvhich vve ſhall fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the ſacred Virgin to excell, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all other vertues, &amp; by the to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the holy Ghoſt, for the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> canonized a liuing Saint, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:18588:84"/>led <hi>Bleſsed: Beata quae credidisti quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam perficientur in te quae dicta ſunt tibi à Domino:</hi> Bleſſed art thou who haſt beleeued, becauſe in thee ſhalbe perfected thoſe myſteries vvhich were declared vnto thee from our Lord. For doubtleſſe ſhe had moſt excellent actes of faith, concerning the high Myſtery of the Incarnation eſpecially, and therfore as one truly faithfull vve may inuocate her holy and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling aſſiſtance, ſaying, <hi>Virgo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis ora pro nobis,</hi> faithfull Virgin, pray for vs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly we may conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Fidelity as it doth import a certaine kind of aſſurance of one friend towards another, wherby the one is fully perſwaded of his friends loue &amp; help in all things, ſo long as he keepeth himſelfe
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:18588:85"/>within the bonds and limits of a true friend. And of the fidelity of our B. Lady, and louing mother, we need not doubt, who is moſt ready to help &amp; comfort vs in all our miſeries, tribulations, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fflictions, if our ſelues by our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, and little reſpect vnto her, deſerue not the repulſe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore keeping our fidelity with her ſweet Sonne, and herſelfe, we may aſſure our ſelues of her fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity towards vs, at all tymes, in all occaſions, and in all our buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes we ſhall alwayes find her <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go fidelis,</hi> a faithful Virgin.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly we may conceau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fidelity as it doth ſignify the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full accompliſhing of all buſine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> committed to our charge: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which ſenſe our Sauiour ſpeaket<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Parable of the talents, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulating
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:18588:85"/>the diligent labours of his faithfull ſeruant, <hi>Euge ſerue bone &amp; fidelis, quia inpauca fuisti fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis, ſuper multa te conſtituam:</hi> Well, good and faithfull ſeruant becauſe thou haſt byn truſty ouer a little, I will make thee ſteward ouer much. And in this ſenſe how worthily the B. Virgin is ſaid to be <hi>faithfull,</hi> will eaſely appeare, if vve conſider aright hovv profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably ſhe did imploy al her rare ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, wherwith her bleſſed So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne had endued her. For what guifts either of Nature or Grace, what talents either naturall or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall (in all which ſhe did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound) did ſhe not fully imploy in the ſeruice of God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of her neighbour, whoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtudy was to pleaſe the one, and help the other, &amp; therfore had
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:18588:86"/>the only priuiledge neuer to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him, or be wanting to them? So as we knowing her loue no leſſe towards vs now, then it was vvhilſt ſhe liued, and her povver far greater, do confidently ſay, <hi>Virgo fidelis, ora pro nobis,</hi> faithfull Virgin, pray for vs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly we may contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate hovv Fidelity doth ſignify the ſtrict band of true loyalty bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvixt true and lawfull ſpouſes: which if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider in the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin towards <hi>S. Ioſeph,</hi> it may ſerue for a mirrour to all vertuous and godly ſpouſes: but if vve weigh the matcheleſſe example of her conſtant fidelity towards the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, to whome by ſpeciall grace, and holy vow, ſhe was eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed; it will ſo farre paſſe the ſhort reach of our weake vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:18588:86"/>that we ſhall be no more able to view the perfection therof, then the ſeely Bat, or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meleſſe owle is able to gaze vpon the glittring beames of the ſunne; yet may we with all humility ſay, <hi>Virgo fidelis, ora pro nobis,</hi> faithfull Virgin, pray for vs; ſince in all thoſe ſenſes of Fidelity, vve find her to haue the chiefeſt place. <hi>Aue Maris ſtella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XXI. MEDITATION. <hi>Speculum Iuſtitiae, ora pro nobis.</hi> Mirour of Iuſtice, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IVSTICE in this place doth not ſo much import the ſpeciall vertue of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> as a generall col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of all vertues togeather, wherby a man doth perfectly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:18588:87"/>himſelfe to the will of God in all things, and is therfore ſaid to be <hi>Iuſt.</hi> In which ſenſe to call our bleſſed Lady <hi>Mirour of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,</hi> is as much as to ſay, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect patterne of all vertue,<note place="margin">Ambr. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Virgin.</note> becauſe in her (as out of S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> we haue noted) <hi>velut in ſpeculo refulget ſpecies caſtitatis &amp; forma virtutis:</hi> as in glaſſe the beauty of Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and forme of all vertue ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Wherfore in this tytle we are to conſider the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> as the perfect modell of all our actions, becauſe by this we ſhall moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſee, what is to be followed, what to be eſchewed, what to be imbraced, what reiected: final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly how to order our liues and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the greater honour &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God. We muſt therfore look
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:18588:87"/>into this Glaſſe, not for curioſity to behold our beauty, but with earneſt deſire to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our faults, we muſt conſider her excellent vertues as the aboue named Saint did, when he wrote,<note place="margin">Ambr. vbi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> that ſhe <hi>was humble in mind, graue in ſpeach pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in iudgment, ſparing in words, ſtudious in reading, repoſing her hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full truſt not in the vncertainty of riches, but in the deuout prayers of the poore: ſhe was willing to worke, baſhfull in ſpeach, accuſtomed to ſeeke not men, but God, for the arbiter of her mind; ſhe hurt no man, ſhe wished well to all, reſpecting her elders, not enuying her equalls, flying boaſting, following reaſon, and louing vertue.</hi> This and much more to this effect doth S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> write, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may ſee, that moſt worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the B. Virgin is ſaid to be, <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:18588:88"/>Iuſtitiae,</hi> the Mirrour of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How carefull would any gentle woman be, if ſhe were to ſpeake in the preſence of a great Perſon, to view herſelfe in a glaſſe once, and many tymes, leaſt any ſpot or blemiſh in her face, any fault or diſorder in her attyre, might make her leſſe gratefull in his ſight, then either he deſerued, or ſhe could wiſh: and ſhall not we, when we go to ſpeake with the King of Kings, for the better and more decent attyring of our ſoules, looke in this glaſſe of all perfection, and learne to decke &amp; adorne our ſelues in ſuch ſort, that we may not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly with Queen <hi>Hester</hi> deſerue to be inuited with the golden Rod of Gods Mercy, vnto his diuine preſence, but
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:18588:88"/>alſo be made worthy to obtaine of him, what we moſt deſire? Yea, let vs not looke only into this myſtical glaſſe, but alſo let vs vſe it as a powerful help to obtain our wiſhed ſuite and petition: let vs frame our actions according to the liuely portraict of her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent vertues, that we may with greater confidence implore her powerfull ayde: let her be our Patterne and Patroneſſe in life and death: let vs deuotly ſay, <hi>Speculum Iustitiae, ora pro nobis.</hi> Myrrour of al perfection, pray for vs. <hi>Aue Maris stella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="meditation">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:18588:89"/>
               <head>THE XXII. MEDITATION <hi>Sedes Sapientiae, ora pro nobis.</hi> The ſeate of wiſdome, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IT is written by the diuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of the holy Ghoſt, and left for our inſtruction, that <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome built himſelfe a howſe, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propped and borne vp with ſeaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtately Pillars,</hi> which not vnfitly we may apply vnto the Eternal Wiſdome of the Sonne of God, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beautifying and adorning the B. Virgin for his mother, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her indeed <hi>Sedes ſapientiae,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeate of Wiſdome.</p>
               <p>Let vs therfore conſider the ſeauen ſtately Pillars which ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sauiour did erect in this his ſpirituall
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:18588:89"/>Soule, his myſticall ſeate, for doubtleſſe they were the ſeauen guifts, &amp; ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-fould grace of the holy Ghoſt, to wit, <hi>Wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, Counſell, Fortitud Science, Piety &amp; feare of our Lord,</hi> al which how eminent they were in our B. Lady, no true Chriſtian wil cal in queſtion; wherby ſhe became the worthy <hi>ſeate of VViſdome,</hi> the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cely throne of the true <hi>Salomon,</hi> &amp; the holy mother of God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. And for two reaſons vve may call the B. Virgin the <hi>Royall ſeate of VViſdome.</hi> Firſt, in that ſhe was the moſt bleſſed, and ſelected Creature choſen amongſt, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all women, to be his holy mother; in whoſe ſacred wombe he was to take his nyne moneths <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt, and then to be moſt louingly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ded in her tender armes, and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:18588:90"/>ſeated on her lappe, with all reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect vnto him, as her God, and no leſſe loue as to her Sonne; and therfore was the <hi>ſeate of VViſdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond reaſon why ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be ſo intytled, is becauſe, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wiſdome be taken for the grace of the holy Ghoſt, or the ſpiritual dwelling of Chriſt in a ſoule, we ſhall find that neuer in any pure Creature the like aboundance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wiſdome was found, the like graces, fauours, &amp; ſupernaturall gifts. And becauſe ſhe ſo careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept theſe gracious guifts, that ſhe alwayes deſerued to keep God in her bleſſed ſoule; therfore ſhe may more properly be ſaid to be the <hi>ſeate of wiſdome.</hi> For although Chriſt many tymes viſiteth moſt mercifully the vnworthy howſe of our ſoules; yet by reaſon of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:18588:90"/>ſtrange ingratitude, wee do not eſteeme as we ought, the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly company of ſo worthy a gheſt, &amp; the ſingular fauours of ſo ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall a friend, but by our offences we expell him from the howſe of our ſoules, and yeild his rightfull ſeate vnto his vſurping enemy. But our bleſſed Lady was alwaies conſtant, euer true vnto him, and therfore his perpetuall ſeate, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as our Sauiour witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of euery iuſt man,<note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ad eum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niemus, &amp; manſionem apud eum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iemus:</hi> vve vvill come vnto him and make our manſion or place of abroad with him.</p>
               <p>O Bleſſed and euer moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Virgin Mother,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> the Regall ſeat of Eternall wiſdome; Let thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vverfull interceſſion ſo preuayle, vvith thy louing Sonne, that vve
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:18588:91"/>may in ſuch ſort receiue him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hovvſe of our ſoules, that vve do not vngratefully caſt him forth againe; but vvithall honour and reſpect ſo ſerue him in this life, that vve may deſerue to dwell in thoſe heauenly manſions of Eternity. Amen. <hi>Salue Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XXIII. MEDITATION. <hi>Cauſa noſtrae laetitiae, ora pro nobis</hi> Cauſe of our Ioy, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>HEEREVVE are to conſide the great ioy vvhich the B. Virgin brought into the world a her ſacred birth, according to tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which we read in the office of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Natiuity, <hi>Natiuitas tua Dei Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix Virgo, gaudium annunciau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vniuerſo mundo:</hi> Thy Natiuity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:18588:91"/>Virgin Mother of God, hath been the long deſired meſſenger of ioy to all the world: for of thee is borne the ſome of Iuſtice, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the former curſe, brought a generall bleſſing vnto vs all. Yet for the better vnderſtanding of the greatnes of the ioy we all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eiued by her happy comming, it vvill be good to make vſe of this contemplation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Imagine after a long and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edious vvinter, hovv gratefull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he approach of a pleaſant ſpring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth ſeeme, not only vnto man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut euen vnto brute beaſts &amp; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> birds, yea in ſome ſort to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery plants, and the earth it ſelf, vvho veſteth herſelfe in nevv ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arell to vvelcome the neere ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roach of the gladſome Sunne, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e pretty birds in their la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:18588:92"/>df the like, to ſhevv the greatnes oo their ioy, vvith their beſt mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or els conſider how grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is the beautifull breaking of a fayre morning after a darke tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous night, telling vs vvith a gladſome bluſh, that the ioy ful Planet, the Sunne, is neere a hand.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Ponder moreouer hovv comfortable vvas the commin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Iudith</hi> to the ſorrovvfull gate of beſeiged <hi>Bethulia,</hi> vvhen ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought them certaine nevves o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their preſent deliuery, and futu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſafety. Then apply all this to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> B. Virgin, cauſe of our ioy, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> after ſo long and tendious a wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſinne, and vvickednes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> her happy comming into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> world, did ſignify vnto, vs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:18588:92"/>the Lambe of God who taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay the ſinnes of the world, was novv neere at hand, &amp; that the bright ſhyning lampe of heauen, would ſpread ere long his beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful beams of light vpon the earth, &amp; that the <hi>Sunne of Iustice</hi> would ſhortly appeare vnto vs; that it might be fulfilled as the Prophet had foretold: The people that ſate in darkenes, ſaw great light; and to them that dvvelt in the region &amp; ſhaddovv of death, light is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. Her happy birth was the fore runner of greater light, and her appearing in this world, the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dawning of a bleſſed day: her prudent demeanour, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cariage of farre more profit and comfort vnto vs, then the wonder, and vvonderfull acts of <hi>Iudith</hi> to the <hi>Bethulians.</hi> She to
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:18588:93"/>one people only was the cauſe of ioy; out B. Lady vnto all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſhe vnto one Citty, the B. Virgin vnto al the world brought ioy and gladnes.</p>
               <p>Let vs therfore not only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this great benefit, but let vs encourage our ſelues,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> with greater confidence to inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate her bleſſed Name, and ſay, <hi>Cauſa nostrae laetitiae, ora pro nobis:</hi> Cauſe of our ioy, pray for vs: that as by her perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Sonne of God became man for our redemption; ſo by her holy interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may profit our ſelues by ſo priceleſſe a ranſome. <hi>Salue Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="meditation">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:18588:93"/>
               <head>THE XXIIII. MEDITATION <hi>Vas Spirituale ora pro nobis.</hi> Spirituall veſſell, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>HEERE we call vpon the B. Virgin by the name of <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall veſsell,</hi> to ſignify the great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of her ſpirituall Graces and bleſſings, wherwith ſhe was repleniſhed. We will therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſweet odours of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine veſſell. It is ſaid,
<q>Quo ſemel est imbutarecens, ſeruabit odorem, testa diu,—</q> with what ſent, or ſauour a veſſel is firſt ſeaſoned, it will conſerue the ſmell therof a long tyme. If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we conſider the firſt ſauour of diuine Grace wherwith this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall veſſell was ſo aboundantly
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:18588:94"/>ſeaſoned in her firſt Conception, which was neuer after loſt, but increaſed almoſt without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; we ſhall not meruayle at this tytle of <hi>Spirituall veſsell,</hi> or diuine Tabernacle of the Holy Ghoſt. For albeit ſhe was full of grace when the Angell came to deliuer his heauenly Embaſſage; yet the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the holy Ghoſt was promiſed vnto her, and the protection of the moſt high to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her. Moreouer the day of <hi>Pentecost</hi> the ſame holy Spirit deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended vpon her in more ample manner then any of the reſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed a veſſell more capable of ſuch diuine influence, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny els, and therfore moſt worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intytled <hi>Vas Spirituale,</hi> a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall veſſell.</p>
               <p>They vſed in the Temple cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:18588:94"/>conſecrated veſſells dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the ſeruice of God, and could not be applyed to any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane vſe without the cryme of Sacriledge; and the like is now of the conſecrated Chalices and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy veſſells. Our B. Lady was a <hi>Spirituall veſſell</hi> conſecrated only to the ſeruice of God, and would haue deemed it a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning of his diuine veſſell, if ſhe ſhould haue admitted the leaſt cogitation of any thought that might haue been vnſeemely in his eyes.</p>
               <p>How great was the cryme of <hi>Nabuchodonoſor,</hi> that tooke ſuch veſſells from the holy Temple of <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> and how ſeuerely his ſon <hi>Baltaſſar</hi> was puniſhed for the prophane vſe he put them vnto,<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> let the Scripture be witnes. But
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:18588:95"/>far greater puniſhment may we aſſuredly perſwade our ſelues is layd vp for ſuch as eyther ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe this ſacred Veſſell, or not giue that duely deſerued reſpect vnto her which they ought. For if God ſo ſeuerely puniſhed the prophaning of his veſſells of gold and ſiluer; what will he do when his holy mother ſhalbe robbed of her right, and the moſt worthy veſſell in the world be abuſed? And on the contrary ſide, vvhat benefits ſhall they receiue at his bountifull hands, who, with all religious reuerence and duty call vpon her, and eſteem her as ſhe is indeed a Spirituall veſſell, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Temple, a diuine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, a gratious Queene, a louing mother and a powerfull Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor for all ſinners, who deuoutly
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:18588:95"/>come vnto her Sonne by her. Let vs by this ſpirituall tytle call for her ayde, <hi>Vas Spirituale, ora pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>obis,</hi> Spirituall veſſell, pray for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s; that we may be alwaies of the number of thoſe, who loue &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee, and who deſire to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance thy holy name, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of thy bleſſed Sonne ſweet leſus. Amen. <hi>O glorioſa Dominae.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XXV. MEDITATION. <hi>Vas Honorabile, ora pro nobis.</hi> Honorable Veſſell, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>THIS Honourable tytle doth many and diuers wayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate vnto vs the dignity of our B. Mother. For if we looke with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> to the powerfull act
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:18588:96"/>of Predeſtination, we ſhall find ſome veſſells of Gold, ſome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Clay, ſome of Honour, others o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Contumely, ſome Elect, ſome Reprobate: amongſt the which elect we ſhal find the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin moſt highly ſeated, &amp; therfore by a certaine kind of excellency ſhe may be ſaid <hi>Vas Honorabile,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> honourable veſſell.</p>
               <p>Furthermore ſome veſſells there are which be dedicated on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Emperours, or Kinges vſe, and therfore honorable veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells: and ſuch we ſhall find the B. Virgin to be, and ſo much the more honourable, by how much the Emperour and King of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen (whom ſhe only ſerued) is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to aduance her to more noble ſeruices. If they be called <hi>Ladies of Honour,</hi> who attend about the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:18588:96"/>Queenes perſon; how much more the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> who attended on God himſelfe, ſhould be eſteemed Honourable, and as ſo pretious a Iewell be accounted worthy of Reuerence &amp; Honour.</p>
               <p>Againe, if the word <hi>Honorable</hi> be taken in that ſenſe vvhich vve ſpake of, when we treated of the honour due vnto her in Heauen, we haue already declared in the XVI. Meditation, what degree of honour belongeth vnto her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other Creatures; ſince therfore by ſo many tytles, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is due, vnto her, all equity and reaſon commands, that vve hould not be ſlacke in rendring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onour, <hi>cui honor debetur,</hi> vnto vvhome honour is due.</p>
               <p>O diuine veſſell of honour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>redeſtinate from all Eternity,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:18588:97"/>and choſen to be the elected mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of him vvho is moſt worthy of all honour; be our faithfull ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate before his diuine Maieſty that we may be alwayes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to defend thine honour, and yield all honour due vnto thee as the Honourable veſſell of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holy Ghoſt, and the moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all women. Amen. <hi>Salu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XXVI. MEDITATION. <hi>Vas inſigne deuotionis, ora pro nobis</hi> Noble veſſell of deuotion, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>BY this worthy Tytle we an taught, what deuotion w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ought to haue towards the bleſſed Queene of Heauen, and mother
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:18588:97"/>of God, who is indeed the ſource, fountaine, and veſſell of deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4.</note> In the Booke of Kings men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of a Veſſell of oyle belonging to a poore widdowe, which did not only remaine full it ſelfe, but alſo filled full many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther veſſells: which not vnfitly doth reſemble the bleſſed Virgin, where barren and dry ſoules may fully refreſh themſelues, and vve ſhall find her ſo liberall and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull a mother, that ſhe will not ceaſe to communicate ſpirituall bleſſings vnto vs, ſo long as vve haue veſſells capable to receiue them.</p>
               <p>If a veſſell ſhould be placed in the midſt of a market, full of gold with free licence for al poore and needy people to repaire thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to releeue their wants: if
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:18588:98"/>any ſhould be found ſo negligen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and careleſſe as not to ſeeke this only meanes, to make himſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> truly rich; he ſhould not only b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iudged worthy to liue in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer miſery, but rightly be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of ſloth and folly. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we caſt our eyes vpon this diuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and noble veſſell, the B. Virgin we ſhall ſee that Almighty Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath placed her firſt in his mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phant Church as a miraculous veſſell of deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vnto whome all that wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch heauenly liquor, may wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> confidence approach; and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only beſprinckle, but euen po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wre full ſhowers of deuotion v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their dry &amp; thirſting ſoules<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which do, and euer will mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſweetly flow from this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full veſſell of deuotion.</p>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:18588:98"/>
               <p> In this Celeſtiall veſſell the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cient Fathers dipped their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and deuout pennes, when they left vnto vs ſo many, &amp; moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orthy monuments of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>full ſeruice to her bountifull li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erality towards them. With this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euotion to this ſacred Queene, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he vndaunted ſpirit of <hi>S. Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was confirmed; the diuine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eits of <hi>S. Denis</hi> graced; the witty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entences of <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed: the graue ſayings of <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> beautified; the learned wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings of S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> honoured; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he illuminated mind of S. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lme</hi> enlightned; the mellifluous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ermons of S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſweetned; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he burning hart of the Seraphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all doctor S. <hi>Bonauenture,</hi> in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned; finally the learned men of al <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ges, were beſprinkled with this
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:18588:99"/>heauenly dew. Let vs not therfore b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our owne wilfull blindnes loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo great a treaſure, and depri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelues of ſo ſoueraigne a remedy but let vs deuoutly, or with deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of deuotion, ſay, <hi>Vas inſigne deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, ora pro nobis,</hi> Noble veſſe of deuotion pray for vs. <hi>Aue M<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris stella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XXVII. MEDITATION. <hi>Roſa mystica, ora pro nobis.</hi> Myſticall Roſe, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>OMITTING many prope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Roſe which mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt aptly be applyed vnto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> B. Virgin, I will only inſiſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon three or foure, not to exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my wonted breuity.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:18588:99"/> 1. Firſt the Roſe is moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifull to behould, and moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to the eye, eſpecially being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewed with ſome ſweet morning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower, which if we apply to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſſed Lady, we ſhall find that, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> naturall beauty none came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eere vnto her, or could be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ared with her, as we haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy proued. And for the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance of heauenly graces, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>holſome ſhowers of bleſſings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owred vpon her, we haue alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eclared how farre ſhe did, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth excell all other creatures.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſecond property wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our bleſſed Queene reſembles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Roſe, is in the ſweet fragrant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell: for as the Roſe is as it were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Queene of flowers, by reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f it ſweet perfuming ſmell; ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e B. Virgin, aboue all women
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:18588:100"/>was moſt gratefull vnto God, &amp; the fragrant odours of her ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vertues, as a moſt excellent ſme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> haue filled the whole Church with ſweetnes, according to that ſaying of S. <hi>Paul, Chriſti bonus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> dor ſumus in omni loco:</hi> we are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good odour of Chriſt in eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place: which is verified chiefly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Queene of heauen.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third reſemblance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this dainty flower is in colour: fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as ſome are white, ſome red, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers damaske; ſo our holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church doth preſent o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Bleſſed Lady vnto vs, ſometym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> white, as in her imaculate Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; ſometymes red, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> her vnſpotted purification, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as old <hi>Simeon</hi> did propheſy vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her, that the ſword of Grie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould pierce and wound her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:18588:100"/>to wit the bitter paſſion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her louing Sonne, for whome ſhe grieued ſo much, that as many le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rned Wryters witnes; <hi>plus quàm martyrfuit,</hi> ſhe was more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yred. Other whiles ſhe appeares <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n damaske, as in the admirable Annunciation, where doubtles with a comely bluſh ſhe pleaded with the Angel about the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of her Chaſt Virginity, which when ſhe vnderſtood it ſhould be kept vnſpotted, ſhe moſt willingly admitted of the Embaſſage.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly a Roſe hath it birth, or as we ſay, ſpringeth from thornes, and amongſt them it groweth vp to perfection: which may be applyed to our bleſſed La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in two ſenſes. Firſt, that ſhe ſprong from the race of ſinners,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:18588:101"/>
                  <hi>ſicut lilium inter ſpinas,</hi> as a lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or roſe amongſt thornes. For albeit her parents were holy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; yet not ſo holy, as they could altogeather auoyd the name o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſinners, the only priuiledge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt and his Bleſſed Mother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Secondly, as the roſe groweth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſharpe thornes; ſo the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Virgin grew vp in vertue, amidſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many harſh and ſharpe mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and heauy Croſſes: in ſo much that ſhe is compared to the Roſe-bed, <hi>quaſi plantatio roſae i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hierico:</hi> like the planting or plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bed of a roſe in <hi>Hierico,</hi> for the roſe tree the longer it groweth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the greater and ſharper are the pricks it beareth; and the Bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Virgin the longer ſhe liued, the more her mortifications did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, that ſhe might well ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:18588:101"/>that all her life was <hi>Crux &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrium,</hi> a Croſſe and martyr dome. And by theſe properties it may eaſily be gathered: how fitly the patterne of all perfection, and the model of patience is compared to the dainty roſe, and therfore my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically we ſay, <hi>Roſa Myſtica, ora pro nobis,</hi> Myſticall Roſe pray for vs. Amen. <hi>Salue Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XXVIII. MEDITATION. <hi>Turis Dauidica, ora pro nobis.</hi> Tower of Dauid, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IN the fourth Chapter of the <hi>Canticles</hi> the vnſpotted beauty of the Holy Church in diuers places is deſcribed; and in the fourth verſe her <hi>Necke</hi> is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:18588:102"/>to the Tower of <hi>Dauid,</hi> built for defence: and moreouer it is ſaid, <hi>Mille clypei pendent ex ea, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis armatura fortium;</hi> a thowſand ſheilds hange theron, all the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of ſtrong and valiant men. Now let vs ſee, for what reaſon our Bleſſed Lady is called <hi>Turris Dauidica,</hi> the Tower of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt may be, becauſe heere we read that the <hi>Necke</hi> of the Church is compared to a To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; and we haue ſaid before that as Chriſt is the <hi>Head</hi> of the Church, ſo the B. Virgin is the <hi>Necke,</hi> through which all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all food deſcendeth to the whole body of the Church: therefore this Tower of <hi>Dauid</hi> is moſt fitly applyed vnto her, and ſhe moſt worthily ſaid to be the tower of Dauid.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:18588:102"/> 2. Secondly this Tower of <hi>Dauid</hi> was a Tower built for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and therfore a thowſand ſhields did ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g on it, &amp; al kind of armor for ſtrong men; which if we accomodat vnto this holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the B Virgin, we ſhall find that ſhe was a ſtately Tower, by reaſon of her height in vertue, &amp; ſtrong by reaſon of her Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which neuer fayled; and for this ſhe is ſaid to tread the <hi>moone vnder her feete,</hi> which is the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole of Inconſtancy. A thouſand ſhields are alwaies ready and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared; becauſe as the diuell hath a thowſand crafty ſleights to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue; ſo hath this Bleſſed Tower as many diuine plotts to preuent him, which by her rare example ſhe hath left vnto vs, with al kind of Armor, both offenſiue and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:18588:103"/>to withſtand the might &amp; force of our ſtronge aduerſary, vvho, as the holy Patriarch <hi>Iob</hi> vvitneſſeth, is ſo potent, that no povver on earth can be compared vnto him. Therfore vvith great reaſon vve fly vnto this ſtrong &amp; inuincible Tower, to cal for ayde, to ſeeke vveapons, to arme our ſelues, againſt the fierce aſſaults of ſo cruel an enemy, ſaying once and many tymes, <hi>Turris Dauidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, ora pro nobis,</hi> Tower of <hi>Dauid</hi> pray for vs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another reaſon vvhy the bleſſed Virgin is named <hi>Turris Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidica,</hi> the Tovver of <hi>Dauid,</hi> is, becauſe as it is ſaid of the Church in generall; ſo it may be applied to euery iuſt and vertuous perſon in particuler, and eſpecially to the B. Virgin, who in all vertue and
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:18588:103"/>Religion was moſt excellent; yea ſo, <hi>per excellentiam,</hi> as we ſay, that ſhe may be called the Tovver of <hi>Dauid,</hi> for the reaſons afore na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p>Wherfore O Bleſſed Virgin,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> O ſtrong and mighty Tower, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadovv of thy defence we fly<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for ſuccour. Holy Mary, help thoſe that are in miſery, ſtrengthen thoſe that faint, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thoſe that grieue; finally pray for vs all, that vnder ſo ſtronge a tower vve may be able to defend our ſelues from our deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the world, the fleſh, and the Diuell. Amen. <hi>Salue Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="meditation">
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:18588:104"/>
               <head>THE XXIX. MEDITATION. <hi>Turris Eburnea ora pro nobis.</hi> Tovver of Iuory, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>THIS tytle declareth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. For as Iuory is rare and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and therfore a Tower built of it, muſt needs be of great eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeme and ſtrength; ſo the Bleſſed Queen of heauen is of very great eſteeme and account; not only in the ſight of God, (which is truly to be great) but alſo in the ſight of Angells and men, worthy to be admired. But becauſe we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Tower, we wil novv conſider vvhy ſhe is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Iuory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:18588:104"/> 1. Iuory amongſt other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties hath this for one, that the older it is, the more it turnes to a beautifull red, or ruddy colour; as vve read in prayſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the old <hi>Nazarets,</hi> that thy vvere <hi>rubicundiores ebore antiquo,</hi> more ruddy then the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Iuory; vvhich property be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitts beſt the Bleſſed Virgin, who the longer ſhe liued in this mortall life, the more ſhe ſuffered; and as her Croſſes did increaſe, ſo the more ſhe drevv to the ruddy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Martyrdome: and the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er ſhe came vnto ſo high a degree of loue and fortitude, the more her golden Charity did ſhine throughout the vvorld; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt fitly ſhe is compared not only to <hi>Iuory,</hi> but euen vnto the ancient <hi>Iuory,</hi> vvhen it is in
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:18588:105"/>greateſt beauty and vvorth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another excellent vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Iuory is, to expell poyſon from the infected vvaters, vvhich is the cauſe (as ſome do vvrite) that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other beaſts vvhere the vvater<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> often be poyſoned by venemou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſerpents, vſe not to drinke vntil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Vnicorne hath dipped in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> horne which expelleth al poyſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and leaueth the waters as whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome as before: which property if we apply to the Bleſſed Virgin we ſhall ſee that no waters of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation can be hurtfull to thoſe who ſet her Heroicall example o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Patience before them. For as the wood that <hi>Moyſes</hi> caſt into the bitter vvater, made it ſvveet and ſauoury; ſo no Croſſes ſo bitter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſtaſtfull, but by meditation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her excellent life, will be made
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:18588:105"/>ſweet and pleaſant.</p>
               <p>O Bleſſed Virgin, be our <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uory</hi> Tovver of defence, be our Citty of Refuge,<note place="margin">Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium.</note> for <hi>ſub tuum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidium confugimus,</hi> vnto thy holy protection vve fly; let not the ſtrong aſſaults of our enemies da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt vs, nor the fierce encounters of our aduerſaryes diſcourage vs; but with thy powerfull interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion help vs, that to the greater glory of thy ſweet Sonne, and further profit of our own ſoules, we may ſtand immoueable in the ſeruice of God, &amp; dayly increaſe in deuotion towards thee. Amen. <hi>O glorioſa Domina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="meditation">
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:18588:106"/>
               <head>THE XXX. MEDITATION. <hi>Domus aurea ora pro nobis.</hi> Golden howſe, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IN this pretious tytle, the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Charity of the B. Virgin is inſinuated. For, as we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready proued, the famous Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> built by <hi>Salomon,</hi> and all couered with gold, was a type or figure of the bleſſed Virgin. And as that Temple was a Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Howſe, built for God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; ſo was the Bleſſed Virgin a ſpirituall and myſticall howſe, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned and adorned for the diuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Temple of the holy Ghoſt, and Bride-chamber of Chriſt; yea for an elected howſe and hoſpitall
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:18588:106"/>for the Bleſſed Trinity. She is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſaid to be of gould, by reaſon of her burning Charity, and infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming loue, ſignified by gould. And as Gould excelleth all other mettalls: ſo doth the Queene of Angells, ſurpaſſe all other pure Creatures.</p>
               <p>By this we may gather, how different are the wayes of God from the wayes of men, and how far diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his thoughts from ours. <hi>Herod</hi> had his ſtately Pallace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned richly in outvvard ſhevv; Chriſt his poore mother richly bedecked with inward vertues. The eies of men iudge by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward face; the eyes of God by the inward hart; therfore the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Pallace of <hi>Herod</hi> is left; this celeſtial howſe of God choſen; for though the Sonne of the Bleſſed
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:18588:107"/>Virgin had howſe to hide his head, (as himſelfe witneſſeth) ſpeaking of an earthly habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet he neuer wanted this Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Chappel, this worthy howſe, his deuout mother, to intertaine him, with all loue and tender af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
               <p>Since therfore we haue in this world, no permanent howſe of aboad, no certaine Citty to inhabite, and dwell in, for any long tyme (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> wryteth;) let vs endeauour all to follow the vertuous life of this ſpirituall and myſticall howſe, that we may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deſerue to be a howſe, wherin Chriſt may reſt: that intertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him in our ſoules by grace in this life, we may be made heire of glory in the next. Amen. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Maris ſtella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="meditation">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:18588:107"/>
               <head>THE XXXI. MEDITATION. <hi>Foederis arca, ora pro nobis.</hi> Arke of the Couenant, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IN the old Law in diuers places is mentioned the <hi>Arke of the Couenant,</hi> made by <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and by Gods expreſſe Commaund, the forme, ſcituation, and all the reſt belonging vnto it: we will briefly conſider, what wood it was made of, and how it was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with gold, what was kept in it, and ſome properties therof, which we will apply to this our myſticall Arke, the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt <hi>Moyſes</hi> made this Arke of <hi>Settim</hi> wood,<note place="margin">Deut. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> which is
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:18588:108"/>called incorruptible, by reaſon of the longe tyme that it remay neth vncorrupted, and this Arke by Gods ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was to be couered all ouer, both within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, with pure Gold. Heere vve may conſider how fittly this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured bleſſed Virgin, who thought made of the corruptible Maſſe wherof all men be compoſed; yet by the Eternall wiſdome of God preſerued from all taint of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, both in body and ſoule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> couered ouer with pure Gold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> within and without, becauſe he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> burning Charity within did giue ſo faire a luſtre to all her outward actions, that ſhe did ſeeme to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the fayreſt Gold. And as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Arke was a Crown of the ſame pure and maſſy gold; ſo ouer the bleſſed Virgins heauenly head
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:18588:108"/>did hang that vnſpekable Crown of Glory, from all Eternity pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for her, which ſhe now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,<note place="margin">Deut. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> that in the <hi>Arke of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant</hi> were kept the Tables of the ten Commaundments, as a witnes againſt thoſe that ſhould afterward rebell; and alſo there was kept a certain meaſure of the <hi>Manna,</hi> in remembrance of ſo great a benefit done vnto the Choſen people of <hi>Iſraell:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> So in the Bleſſed Virgins ſacred breſt was layd vp the table of thoſe ten Commaundements which ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies kept moſt inuiolable, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe who ſhall deny, that they are able to be kept by any.</p>
               <p>And as for the <hi>Manna,</hi> we know ſhe had the keeping of the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:18588:109"/>Celeſtiall <hi>Manna,</hi> Chriſt Ieſus, the true food of our hungry ſoules, and a memoriall of his trueſt loue, and one of his greateſt benefitts done vnto vs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Beſides this, the Arke coming into the waters of <hi>Iordan,</hi> they gaue place for the Children of Iſraell to paſſe ouer without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny danger: which ſignifies the B. Virgins powerfull help, ſtaying the waters of tribulation from the hurtfull purſuite of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, making them to paſſe as ſecure as if they walked on dry land.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And laſtly the Arke with it preſence made the Idoll <hi>Dagon</hi> fall flat downe before it; it was a terrour vnto the enemies of God; and the curious beholders of it, were not a little puniſhed
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:18588:109"/>for their fault: ſo the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin hath, and is the deſtroyer of Idolatry, the terrour vnto the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Church, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere Chaſtizer of thoſe who be more curious then wiſe, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters belonging to her.</p>
               <p>Behould then, how fittly ſhe is compared to the <hi>Arke of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant,</hi> who is alſo ready to help vs, to keep the Couenant vve haue made with God, both in the ſpiritual generation of Baptiſme, as alſo in our good purpoſes, vowes, and all other deuotions wherein we giue our ſelues to God Let vs therfore deuoutly cal vpon her holy Name by this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy tytle, &amp; ſay, <hi>Foederis Arca, ora pro nobis,</hi> Arke of the Couenant pray for vs. <hi>Salue Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="meditation">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:18588:110"/>
               <head>THE XXXII. MEDITATION. <hi>Ianua Caeli, ora pro nobis.</hi> Gate of heauen, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>THIS Metaphoricall ſpeach doth ſignify vnto vs, that as into ſtronge walled Citties there is no hope of entrance, but by the gate: ſo he that prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to enter into the glorious Citty of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Hieruſalem, muſt knock at this beautifull gate the Bleſſed Virgin, who therfore by the holy Church is ſo intytled, as in that diuine hymne <hi>Aue Marris ſtella,</hi> ſhe is ſaid to be <hi>Felix caeli porta,</hi> the happy gate of heauen: and in the Anthym <hi>Aue regina Coelorum,</hi> we ſay, <hi>Salue radix ſalue porta, ex qua
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:18588:110"/>mundo lux est orta:</hi> All hayle o B. roote, all hayle o heauenly gate. And conformable to this in theſe deuout Letanies compoſed in her honor, we ſalute her by the name of <hi>Ianua Cali,</hi> gate of heauen.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt therfore we may me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate hovv vve are created for Cittizens of heauen, where all our chiefeſt treaſure is layd vp; by ſinne the gate was ſhut againſt vs, as rebells againſt Gods ſacred Lawes, vntill Chriſt by his Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent power did open it again vnto vs, and left this beautyfull gate patent vnto all; that who ſo vvould enter into this blisfull pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, ſhould firſt haue this Gate vvell knovvne, by vvhich he might freely enter into Eternall happines; and therfore ſhe is called <hi>Felix caeli porta,</hi> the happy gate
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:18588:111"/>of heauen.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly vve may conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that if this gate be ſhut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, vve can haue but little hope to be able to attain vnto our longing deſire of entrance into the Citty; that is, if our life, manners &amp; conuerſation be ſuch as may hinder our acceſſe vnto this ſtately Gate, vve can haue but ſmall hope of her holy inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; eſpecially if we ceaſe not to offend her Bleſſed So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, which is the only cauſe that vvill bread a deniall to our approach vnto that ſhyning gate, vvho vvith her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>autifull beames of light inuiteth al men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the works of darknes, to the fountaine of light; from the ſnares of death to the fruits of life; &amp; from the valley of extreme miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, vnto the height of all goodnes.</p>
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:18588:111"/>
               <p> O let vs not be ſo blind,<note place="margin">Colloqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> as not to ſee this light; let vs with holy <hi>Moyſes</hi> put off the ſhooes of our earthly affection, and vvith deuout <hi>S. Bernard</hi> fall before her feete; and as theſe deuout Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies doe teach vs, let vs ſay <hi>Ianua Caeli,</hi> gate of Heauen pray for vs: and <hi>Felix caeli porta,</hi> o happy gate of heauen, be not ſhut againſt vs, who ſo much deſire to enter by thee and to reigne with thee, for euer. Amen. <hi>Aue Maris ſtella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XXXIII. MEDITATION. <hi>Stella matutina, ora pro nobis.</hi> Morning ſtarre, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>FOR the better vnderſtanding this worthy tytle, we muſt
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:18588:112"/>conſider firſt what the <hi>Starre of the morning</hi> doth denote vnto vs, and alſo the tyme of its appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, by which we ſhall eaſily perceaue how fittly the Bleſſed Virgin is called <hi>stella matutina,</hi> the morning ſtarre.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt as this bright ſhyning ſtarre of the morning, appearing vnto vs, giueth vs to vnderſtand that the darke night is ended, &amp; the cheerfull day at hand; &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the diſmall clouds of the night were ſhortly to be diſperſed by the comming of a glittering light, to wit the Sunne: Euen ſo the firſt appearing of the Bleſſed Virgin in this world, was a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>running of that great light, her ſweet Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, whoſe ioyfull beames were to expell the myſty darkenes of former igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:18588:112"/>with his ſhyning light of doctrine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly this morning ſtarre doth not only foretell the comming of a light, that ſhould be the ending of a ſad and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly night, but alſo the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a moſt ioyfull day: ſo the happy birth of the Bleſſed Virgin, did foretell vnto the world, that happy day, that now was at hand, when the Angell ſhould denounce vnto the whole world, and firſt vnto the poore watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſheepheards, <hi>gaudium magnum quod erit in omni populo,</hi> the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy which ſhould not be confined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed to the land of <hi>Iury</hi> only, but ſhould be common to al Nations, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mni populo,</hi> to wit, the birth of Chriſt, Sauiour and redeemer of mankind.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="192" facs="tcp:18588:113"/> 3. Againe, the day-ſtarre ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth more bright and light ſome, then the reſt of the ſtarr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that ſhyned before in the night and the Bleſſed Virgin was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brightnes of ſanctity and cleerne of vertues, beyond all Stars, that is, all the Saints that went before or came after her (her Sonne al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> waies excepted, as in al ſuch ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches is moſt fit:) and thus by this glittering light, we may eaſily ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; truly ſay, <hi>nox praeceſſit, dies aut appropinquauit:</hi> that, the night i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> paſt and the day drawes nigh; &amp; therefore vſing the holy Apoſtle Counſell, let vs caſt away th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> workes of darknes, and arme our ſelues with light; and as at myd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day, let vs walke honeſtly in ſigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of all the world, for in ſuch work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we ſhall be ſure to haue this B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:18588:113"/>ſtarre to guide and conduct vs; which God graunt. Amen. <hi>Aue Maris stella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XXXIIII. MEDITATION. <hi>Salus infirmorum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Health of the ſicke, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>ALL manner of ſicknes may be reduced to two kindes of Infirmities; the one corporall, that vexeth and ſometyme taketh away the life of the body; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirituall, which weakeneth and ſometyme extinguiſheth the life of the ſoule: of both which, we may eaſily perceaue the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin, to haue been, and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be a ſoueraigne remedy, by which ſhe is iuſtly ſaid to be <hi>Salus
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:18588:114"/>infirmorum,</hi> the health of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, or ſicke.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt then to conſider the Bleſſed Virgins bounty and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality towards ſicke perſons, vve need no further perſuaſion then the manifold examples written by graue Authors of the almoſt infinit miraculous cures wrought by the Bleſſed Queene of Angels, vpon diſeaſed perſons of all ſorts, and of the deuotion of the places, yet extant, with the frequent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of ſicke and weake people vnto them, with miraculous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of their health, when it is more conuenient for their good, or the honour of God. This I ſay may ſerue for ſufficient proofe of this point, for all ſuch as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly diſpoſed towards the B. Virgin.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="195" facs="tcp:18588:114"/> 2. Concerning ſpirituall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, it is not vnknowne to any Catholike, how many miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Conuerſions haue beene wrought by her holy interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; how many therby haue been brought from the very gates of hell, to the happy gate of heauen; euen ſuch as haue almoſt beene ſwallowed vp in the deſperate gulfe of deſpaire; which is an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſigne and token that ſhe is <hi>Salus infirmorum,</hi> the health of the diſeaſed; by her holy interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion obteyning the perfect Cure both of body and ſoule; giuing vs therby full aſſurance, that if vve confidently haue recourſe vnto her, we may obtayne the like be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, if we haue the like deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Salue Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="meditation">
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:18588:115"/>
               <head>THE XXXV. MEDITATION. <hi>Refugium Peccatorum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Refuge of ſinners, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IN the old Law there were many Citties ordeyned by Gods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commaundment, whither men guilty of certaine Crymes, might fly to ſaue their liues, as now in the new Law our Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries are, where offendours may be ſafe from the purſuing enemy. And becauſe the Bleſſed Virgin is a common Refuge, to whome all ſinners may fly, to hide themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, vntill the wrath of God be paſt; therfore ſhe is called and rightly intytled the Refuge of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:18588:115"/>
               <p> The ſumme of this Meditaton may be, to conſider, That theſe forenamed Citties of Refuge were ordeyned for ſuch as caſually did murther their brethren; for if wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully they did commit any ſuch cryme it auayled them nothing at all to fly to the ſaid Citties: So whilſt our ſinnes, be of infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and weakenes, we may with confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce fly vnto her; but if they proceed of obſtinacy and malice, and ſo contynue, we can expect no fauour at her hands, yet in this ſhe ſo excelleth all the foreſaid Citties of Refuge, that although the ſin be of this latter ſort of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate malice; yet if they will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their vnderſtanding, and conforme their will, ſhe is ready to take them vnder her protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and with her powerfull pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:18588:116"/>obtaine them pardon, &amp; bring them againe into the fauour of God. Since therfore ſhe doth not diſdaine to be called <hi>Refuge of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> let vs not be ſo vngratefull and blind, as not to make vſe of ſo friendly an offer, ſo ſtronge a Refuge, and ſo potent an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, but let vs deuoutly fly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her ſaying, <hi>Refugium Peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ora pro nobis:</hi> Refuge of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners pray for vs. <hi>Pater &amp; Aue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XXXVI. MEDITATION. <hi>Conſolatrix afflictorum ora pro nobis.</hi> Comfortreſſe of the afflicted, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>VVE haue ſeene before that this heauenly Queene is a ſoueraigne remedy of the ſicke,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:18588:116"/>the diſeaſe being either corporal or ſpirituall: now we are to conſider how ſhe is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to the afflicted, which will appeare many waies.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt it is a comfort for one that is in affliction, to knovv that ſome others haue paſſed the ſame way; and farre greater to vnderſtand that they paſſed not only vvithout hurt, but vvith great renowne: So in our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt miſeries and calamities if vve looke vpon this comfortable ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, &amp; conſider the rare example ſhe hath left vs, we ſhall find that all we ſuffer or can ſuffer, is but a ſhaddovv to that which ſhe hath vndergone. This then may be the firſt cauſe of comfort to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly it is a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to thoſe that are afflicted,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:18588:117"/>to haue ſome deare and louing friend to take compaſſion of their miſery, where they behould as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were, the image of themſelues, ſuffering in their friends hart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And doubtles the Bleſſed Virgin hath ſuch perfect loue vnto he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true Children, and ſuch tende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> compaſſion of their afflictions<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that ſhe cannot chooſe but in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> manner ſuffer with them; which is exceeding comfort to haue a partaker of our ſorrowes. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit theſe paſſions be not in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, yet ſhe hath perfect notice o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our troubles, and as a moſt louing mother ſeeketh to remedy our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions when it is conuenient for vs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, it is a great refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing to the afflicted, to know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they haue a friend who is able to
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:18588:117"/>deliuer them, if they giue him notice of it, and ſhew that they deſire it. And ſuch is the Bleſſed Virgin alwaies ready to giue vs all comfort, if confidently and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly, as vve ought, vve fly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her. For ſo povverfull is her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, that what ſhe asketh for vs ſhe obteyneth; and ſo great her wiſdome is, that ſhe vvill aske nothing but what is conuenient for our eternall good. If therfore in our afflictions, ſhe doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſuccour vs, we may perſwad our ſelues, that they be more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylable for our ſpirituall good, then al the comforts in the world. And by theſe conſiderations vve may ſee, how truly the B. Virgin is, <hi>Conſolatrix afflictorum,</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortreſſe of the afflicted. <hi>Salue Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="meditation">
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:18588:118"/>
               <head>THE XXXVII. MEDITATION. <hi>Auxiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Christianorum, ora pro nobis.</hi> The help of Chriſtians, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>BY this title all true Chriſtians do acknowledge the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full help of the Bleſſed Virgin in their neceſſities, eſpecially when they vndertake any worthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit for her Bleſſed Sonne; as the conuerſion of Nations, the redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſtian Captiues, or the iuſt defence of their owne Country, againſt the treacherous inuaſions of barbarous people and Infidells; for in ſuch worthy imployments, as the Chriſtians haue alwayes vſed, to ſhew their ſingular deuotion, in the inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:18588:118"/>of our Bleſſed Lady: ſo ſhe hath neuer fayled in ſhewing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler fauours towards them.</p>
               <p>Beſides, we haue other eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies both ſtronger and ſubtiler, againſt whoſe aſſaults we haue more need of her ayde and aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; I meane, the Capitall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of mankind, who neuer cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to deface the very image of God in vs, &amp; who by her power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full interceſſion and holy prayers is put to confuſion, yea by the on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly naming of our B. Lady, which he is not able to endure. And la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly, though we were free from all outward foes; yet ſhall we neuer want a domeſticall enemy, whoſe diſordered appetites &amp; diſhoneſt deſires do ſeldome, or neuer beare ſway in thoſe, who are truely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted to the B. Virgin.</p>
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:18588:119"/>
               <p> To conclude as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> wryteth,<note place="margin">Bern. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eſt.</note> Let vs in al tribulations, in all ſtraites, in all dangers, call vpon her Bleſſed name, and vve ſhall proue in our ſelus how righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly ſhe may be, and is intytled <hi>Auxilium Chriſtianorum,</hi> the ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and helper of Chriſtians: But that we may the better inioy this ſoueraigne help, we muſt examin our ſelues, that we be not, as <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>nomine Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, re vani,</hi> in name Chriſtians, but indeed vayne, and deuoyd of all true Chriſtianity: for ſuch haue put a clowde before the bright beames of her fauour, that they cannot ſhine vpon them. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O Bleſſed Virgin help vs, that we may be truly ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Chriſt and true Chriſtians; for then we ſhall neuer be deſtitute of thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:18588:119"/>help, who art the ſheild of all good Chriſtians. <hi>O glorioſa Domina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XXXVII. MEDITATION. <hi>Regina Angelorum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queene of Angells, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>IN theſe tytles following our B. Lady is called <hi>Queene of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, Queene of Patriarks, Queene of Prophets,</hi> and the like. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will briefly aſſigne ſome one or two reaſons, why ſhe may be ſaid to be their Queene, for ſome excellency that did ſhine in her, in that kind. As in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Meditation ſhe is intytled Queene of Angells, by reaſon of her vnſpotted and chaſt behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:18588:120"/>wherin ſhe did excell and lead, as we vſe to ſay, an Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall life on earth.</p>
               <p>Secondly as ſhe is now crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Queene of Heauen, ſhe may moſt fitly be called <hi>Queene of An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gells,</hi> becauſe they be the chiefeſt aſſiſtants in that heauenly Court, where ſhe, as Queene and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, ſits exalted aboue them all, and they no doubt moſt prompt and obedient at her will; and by this vve ſalute her in this place, &amp; call her, as indeed ſhe is, <hi>Regina Angelorum,</hi> Queene of Angells. <hi>Aue regina Caelorum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="meditation">
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:18588:120"/>
               <head>THE XXXIX. MEDITATION. <hi>Regina Patriarcharum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queene of the Patriarkes, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>OVR bleſſed Lady may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Queene of Patriarks</hi> in this reſpect, that the high myſtery of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Incarnation was fulfilled in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er; and the chiefeſt Promiſes made vnto them had their effect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n this Bleſſed Queene. Beſides, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er excellent faith of all the myſteries of our faith, did far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed that of the <hi>Patriarkes;</hi> her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eale was greater, her expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more feruorous, her deſires more ardent; that whatſoeuer was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n them prayſe-worthy, was in the B. Virgin in a farre more high
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:18588:121"/>degree, and therfore moſt worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we ſay, <hi>Regina Patriarcharum, ora pro nobis,</hi> Queene of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arks, pray for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XL. MEDITATION. <hi>Regina Prophetarum, ora pro nobis</hi> Queene of Prophets, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>THE holy Prophets, as by their writings we may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, (and their names im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port as much) had great light from Almighty God, concerning the myſteries of our faith; the conuerſion of the world; the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Church; the Birth Death &amp; Reſurrection of Chriſt with the reſt belonging to ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith: but the light that was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:18588:121"/>vnto our bleſſed Lady, did go farre beyond them, her guiftes and propheſy greater, her grace more aboundant, and was indeed the ſhyning ſtar, at which they in their propheſies did but point, as the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth when he ſaith, <hi>Ecce Virgo concipiet,</hi> behold a Virgin ſhall conceaue: and by this ſhe is ſaid Queene of Prophets. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XLI. MEDITATION. <hi>Regina Apostolorum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queene of the Apoſtles, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>BY greater reaſon, ſhe is ſaid to be the <hi>Queene of the Apostles,</hi> then either of <hi>Patriarkes</hi> or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, being (after the Aſcenſion of Chriſt) left amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them as a
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:18588:122"/>Queene to gouerne and direct them, to their exceeding great comfort and conſolation. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the holy Ghoſt was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed their chiefe Directour and Rectour; yet it is like that they did many things by her meanes; as it is thought, that <hi>S. Luke</hi> did write his Ghoſpell, eſpecially concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the infancy of our Sauiour by her direction, though gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned otherwiſe by the holy ſpirit of God. And therfore when ſhe paſſed out of this life, they all came togeather miraculouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned, to celebrate with due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and deuotion, the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rites of their ſoueraigne Queene. Behold therfore, hovv deſeruedly ſhe is called <hi>Queene of the Apostles. Salue Regina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="meditation">
               <pb n="211" facs="tcp:18588:122"/>
               <head>THE XLII. MEDITATION. <hi>Regina Martyrum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queen of Martyrs, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>MOST worthily ſhe is enty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled <hi>Queene of Martyrs,</hi> &amp; that for many reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt becauſe in her life ſhe ſuffered more then any, yea then all the Martyrs togeather, as I haue already proued.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly ſhe may be called <hi>Queen of Martyrs,</hi> by reaſon of the rare example that ſhe left them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And laſtly, becauſe in their agonyes and paſſions, no doubt they had particuler help &amp; comfort from her, whome they called vpon, as we do, <hi>Regina Martyrum, ora pro nobis,</hi> Queene of Martyrs pray for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="meditation">
               <pb n="212" facs="tcp:18588:123"/>
               <head>THE XLIII. MEDITATION. <hi>Regina Confeſſorum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queen of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſours, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>CONFESSOVRS are they, who though they cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the ſublime dignity of Martyrdome, yet with their good life &amp; vertuous actions they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt to be true God and Man, and are ready to dye, if ſo it ſhould pleaſe him, in defence of the leaſt article of his holy doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. And becauſe the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in this point hath gone ſo farre beyond them all, and left them ſo memorable examples of Conſtancy and Fortitude; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe is not only ſayd to be their comforter, as we haue already me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated; but alſo their Queene,
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:18588:123"/>
                  <hi>Regina Confeſſorum,</hi> Queene of Confeſſors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="meditation">
               <head>THE XLIIII. MEDITATION. <hi>Regina Virginum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queene of Virgins, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>OVR Bleſſed Lady hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned euer a perpetual Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and being the firſt that dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated herſelfe vnto God by holy vow of Virginity; became the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entour &amp; foundreſſe of this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall life; and therfore by great reaſon, ſhe is ſaid to be the <hi>Queene of Virgins,</hi> and by which title we daily call vpon her ſaying, <hi>Regina Virginum, ora pro nobis,</hi> Queene of Virgins pray for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="meditation">
               <pb n="214" facs="tcp:18588:124"/>
               <head>THE XLV. MEDITATION. <hi>Regina Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ora pro nobis.</hi> Queen of all Saints, pray for vs.</head>
               <p>BRTEFLY in this tytle we may conſider, that what vertue or excellent guift ſoeuer hath beene eminent in any Saint, hath ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned farre more in our bleſſed La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; yea whatſoeuer naturall or ſupernaturall guift or grace, hath beene in them all togeather, hath byn all at once in this B. Queene; &amp; therfore moſt worthily we ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute her by this renowned tytle of <hi>Queene of all Saints:</hi> and by this deſiring her powerfull prayers, and holy interceſſion, we ſay, <hi>Regina Sanctorum omnium ora pro nobis,</hi> Queene of all Saints pray for vs. Amen. <hi>Aue Maris ſtella</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="215" facs="tcp:18588:124"/>
            <head>THE CONCLVSION, WITH AN APOSTROPHE <hi>to the euer B Virgin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY intention (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and moſt worthy) in theſe ſhort meditations, vvas not to delight your eares with flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing eloquence, which is both beyond my reach, &amp; paſt my skil; but my chiefe purpoſe tending only to the encouragement of ſo Noble a CONGREGATION, ſo happily inſtituted in Honor of the Imaculate Virgin Mary, Mother of God, &amp; the ſatisfaction which
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:18588:125"/>I hoped many other or her deuout Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by reading therof, would find; I was the more willing to let it come to your view in the ſimple attyre wherwith it is veſted.</p>
            <p>For albeit, of it ſelfe, it be ſcarce worthy to be read of any; yet for her ſake, of whome it trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, I deſyre it may diligently be peruſed of many. Wherfore if any thing heerin be found worthy of commendations, let the prayſe be giuen to the true deſeruer; for al that is blame-worthy, is wholly myne; for which I craue, both your pardon for my errour and boldnes, and allſo your prayers, for my future diligence, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment.</p>
            <p>And thou thrice-happy and euer B. Virgin, Mother, Queene &amp; Empreſſe of Heauen &amp; Earth,
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:18588:125"/>whoſe Honour; next after thy ſweet Sonne I moſt intend, in theſe my willing, but weake la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; be thou a Starre to enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thoſe that read them; a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe to inſtruct them, a Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to defend them, and a ſafe Guide to direct them, to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of Eternall bliſſe, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happines. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:126"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OF THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE I. MEDITATION. <hi>Of the Venerable &amp; facred Name of the most B. Virgin, MARIA.</hi> pag. 1.</item>
               <item>The II. Meditation. <hi>Of the ſanctity of the B. Virgin.</hi> pag. 14.</item>
               <item>The III. Meditation. <hi>Sancta Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitrix ora pro nobis.</hi> Holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God, pray for vs. pa. 26.</item>
               <item>The IIII. Meditation. <hi>Sancta Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go Virginum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Holy Virgin of Virgins, pray for vs. pag. 35.</item>
               <item>The V. Meditation. <hi>Mater Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti ora pro nobis.</hi> Mother of Chriſt, pray for vs. pag. 47.</item>
               <item>The VI. Meditation. <hi>Mater diuina gratiae, ora pro nobis.</hi> Mother of
<pb facs="tcp:18588:126"/>diuine grace, pray for vs. pa. 55.</item>
               <item>The VII. Meditation. <hi>Mater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsima, ora pro nobis.</hi> Moſt pure Mother, pray for vs. pag. 62.</item>
               <item>The VIII. Meditation. <hi>Mater Caſtiſſima, ora pro nobis.</hi> Moſt chaſt Mother, pray for vs. pag. 70.</item>
               <item>The IX. Meditation. <hi>Mater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolata, ora pro nobis.</hi> Vndefiled Mother, pray for vs. pag. 75.</item>
               <item>The X. Meditation. <hi>Mater Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merata, ora pro nobis.</hi> Vntouched Mother, pray for vs. pag. 79.</item>
               <item>The XI. Meditation. <hi>Mater a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabilis, ora pro nobis.</hi> Louely Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, pray for vs. pag. 84.</item>
               <item>The XII. Meditation. <hi>Mater Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirabilis, ora pro nobis.</hi> Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Mother, pray for vs. pa. 91.</item>
               <item>The XIII. Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Mater Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris, ora pro nobis.</hi> Mother of the Creatour, pray for vs. pag. 97.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:18588:127"/>
               <item>The XIV. Meditation. <hi>Mater Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natoris, ora pro nobis.</hi> Mother of our Sauiour, pray for vs. pa. 102.</item>
               <item>The XV. Meditation. <hi>Virgo Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiſsima, ora pro nobis.</hi> Moſt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Virgin, pray for vs pa. 107.</item>
               <item>The XVI. Meditation. <hi>Virgo Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neranda, ora pro nobis.</hi> Venerable Virgin, pray for vs. pag. 112.</item>
               <item>The XVII. Meditation. <hi>Virgo Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicanda, ora pro nobis.</hi> Virgin wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of prayſe, pray for vs. p. 118.</item>
               <item>The XVIII. Meditation. <hi>Virgo Potens, ora pro nobis.</hi> Potent Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, pray for vs. pag. 124.</item>
               <item>The XIX. Meditation. <hi>Virgo Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens, ora pro nobis.</hi> Clement Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, pray for vs. pag. 129.</item>
               <item>The XX. Meditation. <hi>Virgo ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis, ora pro nobis.</hi> Faithfull Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, pray for vs. pag. 134.</item>
               <item>The XXI. Meditation. <hi>Speculum
<pb facs="tcp:18588:127"/>Iuſtitiae, ora pro nobis.</hi> Mirrour of Iuſtice, pray for vs. pag. 139.</item>
               <item>The XXII. Meditation. <hi>Sedes Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiae, ora pro nobis.</hi> The ſeate of wiſdome, pray for vs. pag. 144.</item>
               <item>The XXIII. Meditation. <hi>Cauſae noſtrae laetitiae, ora pro nobis.</hi> Cauſe of our Ioy, pray for vs. pag. 148.</item>
               <item>The XXIV. Meditation. <hi>Vas Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituale, ora pro nobis.</hi> Spirituall veſſell, pray for vs. pag. 153.</item>
               <item>The XXV. Meditation. <hi>Vas Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norabile, ora pro nobis.</hi> Honourable Veſſell, pray for vs. pag. 157.</item>
               <item>The XXVI. Meditat. <hi>Vas inſigne deuotionis, ora pro nobis.</hi> Nobleveſ. ell of deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pray for vs. p. 160.</item>
               <item>The XXVII. Meditation. <hi>Roſae myſtica, ora pro nobis.</hi> Myſticall Roſe pray for vs. pag. 164.</item>
               <item>The <hi>XXVIII.</hi> Meditation. <hi>Turris Dauidica, ora pro nobis.</hi> Tower of
<pb facs="tcp:18588:128"/>Dauid, pray for vs. pag. 169.</item>
               <item>The <hi>XXIX.</hi> Meditation. <hi>Turris Eburnea, ora pro nobis.</hi> Tower of Iuory, pray for vs. pag. 174.</item>
               <item>The <hi>XXX.</hi> Meditation. <hi>Domus aurea, ora pro nobis</hi> Golden howſe pray for vs. pag. 178.</item>
               <item>The XXXI. Meditation. <hi>Foederis arca, ora pro nrbis.</hi> Arke of the Couenant, pray for vs. pag. 181.</item>
               <item>The XXXII. Meditation. <hi>Ianua Caeli, ora pro nobis.</hi> Gate of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, pray for vs. pag. 186.</item>
               <item>The XXXIII. Meditation. <hi>Stella matutina, ora pro nobis.</hi> Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtarre, pray for vs. pa. 189.</item>
               <item>The XXXIIII. Meditation. <hi>Salus infirmorum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Health of the ſicke, pray for vs. pa. 193.</item>
               <item>The XXXV. Meditation. <hi>Refugiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Peccatorum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Refuge of ſinners, pray for vs. pag. 196.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:18588:128"/>
               <item>The XXXVI. Meditation. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatrix afflictorum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Comfortreſſe of the afflicted, pray for vs. pag. 198.</item>
               <item>The XXXVII. Meditation. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xilium Christianorum, ora pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</hi> The help of Chriſtians, pray for vs. pag. 202.</item>
               <item>The XXXVIII. Meditation. <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Angeloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queene of Angells, pray for vs. pa. 205.</item>
               <item>The XXIX. Meditat. <hi>Regina Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarcharu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queen of the Patriarks, pray for vs. p. 207.</item>
               <item>The XL. Meditation. <hi>Regina Pro phetarum, oro pro nobis.</hi> Queene of Prophets, pray for vs. p. 208.</item>
               <item>The XLI. Meditation. <hi>Regina A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum, ora pro nobis,</hi> Queene of the Apoſtles, pray for vs. pag. 209.</item>
               <item>The XLII. Meditation. <hi>Regina
<pb facs="tcp:18588:129"/>Martyrum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queene of Martyrs, pray for vs. pag 211</item>
               <item>The XLIII. Meditation. <hi>Regina Confeſſorum ora pro nobis.</hi> Queen of Confeſſours, pray for vs. pag. 212.</item>
               <item>The XLIV. Meditation. <hi>Reginae Virginum, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queene of Virgins, pray for vs. pag. 213.</item>
               <item>The XLV. Meditation. <hi>Regina Sanctorum omnium, ora pro nobis.</hi> Queen of all Saints, pray for vs pag. 214.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18588:129"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
